<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc xml:id="_1"/>
<encodingDesc>
<appInfo>
<application version="0.8.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-06-24T15:41+0000">
<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
</application>
</appInfo>
</encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<body>
<p>Background Mortality statistics are fundamental to public health decision making. Mortality varies by time and location, and its measurement is affected by well known biases that have been exacerbated during the COVID-19 pandemic. This paper aims to estimate excess mortality from the COVID-19 pandemic in 191 countries and territories, and 252 subnational units for selected countries, from Jan 1, 2020, to Dec 31, 2021.</p>
<p>Methods All-cause mortality reports were collected for 74 countries and territories and 266 subnational locations (including 31 locations in low-income and middle-income countries) that had reported either weekly or monthly deaths from all causes during the pandemic in 2020 and 2021, and for up to 11 year previously. In addition, we obtained excess mortality data for 12 states in India. Excess mortality over time was calculated as observed mortality, after excluding data from periods affected by late registration and anomalies such as heat waves, minus expected mortality. Six models were used to estimate expected mortality; final estimates of expected mortality were based on an ensemble of these models. Ensemble weights were based on root mean squared errors derived from an out-of-sample predictive validity test. As mortality records are incomplete worldwide, we built a statistical model that predicted the excess mortality rate for locations and periods where all-cause mortality data were not available. We used least absolute shrinkage and selection operator (LASSO) regression as a variable selection mechanism and selected 15 covariates, including both covariates pertaining to the COVID-19 pandemic, such as seroprevalence, and to background population health metrics, such as the Healthcare Access and Quality Index, with direction of effects on excess mortality concordant with a meta-analysis by the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention. With the selected best model, we ran a prediction process using 100 draws for each covariate and 100 draws of estimated coefficients and residuals, estimated from the regressions run at the draw level using draw-level input data on both excess mortality and covariates. Mean values and 95% uncertainty intervals were then generated at national, regional, and global levels. Out-of-sample predictive validity testing was done on the basis of our final model specification.</p>
<p>Jan 1, 2020, and Dec 31, 2021, totalled 5•94 million worldwide, we estimate that 18•2 million (95% uncertainty interval 17•1-19•6) people died worldwide because of the COVID-19 pandemic (as measured by excess mortality) over that period. The global all-age rate of excess mortality due to the COVID-19 pandemic was 120•3 deaths (113•1-129•3) per 100 000 of the population, and excess mortality rate exceeded 300 deaths per 100 000 of the population in 21 countries. The number of excess deaths due to COVID-19 was largest in the regions of south Asia, north Africa and the Middle East, and eastern Europe. At the country level, the highest numbers of cumulative excess deaths due to COVID-19 were estimated in India (4•07 million [3•71-4•36]), the USA (1•13 million [1•08-1•18]), Russia (1•07 million [1•06-1•08]), Mexico (798 000 [741 000-867 000]), Brazil (792 000 [730 000-847 000]), Indonesia (736 000 [594 000-955 000]), and Pakistan (664 000 [498 000-847 000]). Among these countries, the excess mortality rate was highest in Russia (374•6 deaths [369•7-378•4] per 100 000) and Mexico (325•1 [301•6-353•3] per 100 000), and was similar in Brazil (186•9 [172•2-199•8] per 100 000) and the USA (179•3 [170•7-187•5] per 100 000). Interpretation The full impact of the pandemic has been much greater than what is indicated by reported deaths due to COVID-19 alone. Strengthening death registration systems around the world, long understood to be crucial to global public health strategy, is necessary for improved monitoring of this pandemic and future pandemics. In addition, further research is warranted to help distinguish the proportion of excess mortality that was directly caused by SARS-CoV-2 infection and the changes in causes of death as an indirect consequence of the pandemic.</p>
<p>An accurate measurement of the number of deaths due to the COVID-19 pandemic is crucial for each country and region to understand the magnitude of the pandemic's impact on public health. Accurate measurement of death is also needed to understand the determinants of variation in the infection-fatality ratio across populations, and is a direct input into forecasting the pandemic and investigating alternative policy options. Reported deaths attempt to quantify the magnitude of the COVID-19 pandemic in different populations and locations over time, and they are widely seen as a more reliable indicator for tracking the pandemic relative to reported case rates. 1 However, reported deaths represent only a partial count of total death tolls from the COVID-19 pandemic, and the reliability of reported deaths varies greatly between locations and over time.</p>
<p>Excess mortality due to the COVID-19 pandemic, defined as the net difference between the number of deaths during the pandemic (measured by observed or estimated all-cause mortality) and the number of deaths that would be expected on the basis of past trends in allcause mortality, is therefore a crucial measure of the true toll of the COVID-19 pandemic. Gaps exist between reported and excess deaths related to the COVID-19 pandemic for a number of reasons. First, health-care reporting systems generally do not list COVID-19 as the cause of death without a positive SARS-CoV-2 test, and thus deaths due to COVID-19 will be missed in official counts in locations with low testing capacity. For example, early in the pandemic, before tests were widely available, many deaths due to COVID-19 among older individuals in high-income countries, particularly in long-term care facilities, are unlikely to have been attributed to COVID-19, 2 with evidence of extensive underreporting in many locations. [3][4][5][6] Second, country systems for registering deaths vary in their quality and comprehensiveness, as well as in the definitions used for</p>
<p>Evidence before this study Many attempts have been made to estimate the total number of deaths related to the COVID-19 pandemic. WHO estimated a total of 3 million excess deaths due to the COVID-19 pandemic during the year 2020, although they have not made available excess mortality estimates by location. Numerous studies have examined excess mortality due to COVID-19 for specific countries or subnational units during different stages of the pandemic. Various models have been proposed to estimate expected mortality based on past rates and trends for all-cause mortality. Such modelling approaches include simple count models with fixed effects on week and year; time series-type models including autoregressive integrated moving average (ARIMA) and Holt-Winters models; and simpler assumptions that expected mortality during the pandemic can be assumed to equate to average mortality rates in 2015-19. The World Mortality Dataset provides regularly updated excess mortality estimates for 117 countries and subnational units for a subset of the countries; expected mortality in this dataset is modelled with a linear regression on weekly, monthly, or quarterly death counts with a dummy variable on week, month, or quarter, and year as a continuous variable. The Economist, whose analytical model has not been peer-reviewed, provides the most comprehensive assessment of excess mortality due to COVID-19 to date; they used a machine learning algorithm with a vast list of covariates to produce excess mortality estimates for 187 countries. They provide a global estimate of 18•0 million (95% uncertainty interval 10•9-24•4) excess deaths for the period of Jan 1, 2020, to Dec 27, 2021.</p>
<p>This study makes several important contributions to understanding the full impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on mortality. First, we corrected all-cause mortality data for lags in reporting and for under-registration of death. Second, we excluded weeks with heat waves, for which excess mortality due to COVID would be overestimated due to the large increase in observed mortality from excessive heat during the pandemic. Third, we used an ensemble of six models to predict the expected mortality rate in the absence of COVID-19. Weights in the ensemble were based on the out-of-sample predictive validity of each model. Fourth, for locations without weekly or monthly reported all-cause mortality data, we developed a statistical model that captured the relationship between the key COVID-19-related covariates, such as seroprevalence, infection-detection ratio, and other population-level burden of disease metrics, and excess mortality rate. Fifth, to evaluate the robustness of the model predicting excess mortality, we conducted out-of-sample predictive validity testing, which indicated a small error rate (0•85%). Sixth, by looking comprehensively across countries, we were able to generate estimates of excess mortality for 191 countries and territories, in addition to internally consistent regional and global aggregates. These estimates will form part of the next iteration of the Global Burden of Diseases, Injuries, and Risk Factors Study.</p>
<p>Our estimates of COVID-19 excess mortality suggest the mortality impact from the COVID-19 pandemic has been more devastating than the situation documented by official statistics. Official statistics on reported COVID-19 deaths provide only a partial picture of the true burden of mortality. The difference between excess mortality and reported COVID-19 deaths might be a function of underdiagnosis due to insufficient testing, reporting challenges, or higher than expected mortality from other diseases due to pandemicrelated changes in behaviours or reduced access to health care or other essential services. The gap between estimated excess mortality and reported COVID-19 deaths is much larger in south Asia and sub-Saharan Africa than in other regions. The differences shown between reported COVID-19 mortality and COVID-19-related excess mortality highlight the importance of the use of COVID-19-related excess mortality estimates in policy and in monitoring and evaluation efforts.</p>
<p>counting COVID-19 deaths. Third, among the global medical community, there is no universal agreement as to when a death of someone infected with SARS-CoV-2 should be reported as a death due to COVID-19. Fourth, other factors including political considerations appear to have prevented accurate reporting of deaths in some locations. Fifth, the magnitude and distribution of many other causes of death might have changed because of social, economic, and behavioural responses to the pandemic, including strict lockdowns. Under these conditions, excess mortality can provide a more accurate assessment of the total mortality impact of the COVID-19 pandemic than reported COVID-19 deaths.</p>
<p>Several attempts have been made to estimate excess mortality from COVID-19, although these have generally been limited in geographical scope by the availability of data. WHO has estimated regional excess mortality for the Americas and Europe but has not yet produced countrylevel estimates for these regions. 7 Other country-specific or location-specific studies have evaluated the effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on all-cause mortality for specific locations during different stages of the pandemic. [8][9][10] Such studies have used a variety of models to estimate expected mortality during the pandemic on the basis of past rates and trends in all-cause mortality, making direct comparisons of excess mortality between locations difficult. The Economist, whose estimation model has not been peer-reviewed, produces the only other set of COVID-19-related excess mortality estimates for a uniform time period for a total of 187 countries included in their analysis regardless of vital registration data availability.</p>
<p>In addition to deaths from SARS-CoV-2 infection, social distancing mandates and other pandemic restrictions might have decreased deaths from some diseases and injuries, such as road accidents, [11][12][13] and increased others, such as deaths from chronic and acute conditions affected by deferred care-seeking in overstretched health-care systems, 14,15 relative to expected or baseline conditions. Such changes to baseline patterns of disease and injury death affect the excess mortality from the pandemic; differentiating how much excess mortality is due to SARS-CoV-2 infection and how much is due to other societal, economic, or behavioural changes associated with the pandemic is challenging, especially without detailed data on specific causes of death in many countries. Although separating out the contributors to excess mortality will be extremely important, understanding the total mortality impact of the pandemic is a crucial first step.</p>
<p>Our objective in this study was to estimate, globally and for each of the 191 countries and territories (and 252 subnational units for a subset of nations) included in our analysis, excess deaths due to the pandemic from Jan 1, 2020, to Dec 31, 2021. We leveraged data from locations where all-cause mortality data were available from the periods before and during the pandemic to estimate excess mortality for the study period; we then explored the statistical relationship between excess mortality rate and key covariates including COVID-19 seroprevalence, infection-detection ratio (IDR), and other population health-related metrics such as the Healthcare Access and Quality (HAQ) Index. 16 We used this model to generate location-specific and global estimates of excess deaths due to the COVID-19 pandemic over the study period. Our excess mortality estimates reflect the full impact of the pandemic on mortality around the world, and not only deaths directly attributable to SARS-CoV-2 infection.</p>
<p>Our analysis of excess mortality due to the COVID-19 pandemic from Jan 1, 2020, to Dec 31, 2021, followed four key steps. First, we developed a database of all-cause mortality by week and month after accounting for reporting lags, anomalies such as heat waves, and under-registration of death. Second, we developed an ensemble model to predict expected deaths in the absence of the COVID-19 pandemic for years 2020 and 2021. In location and time combinations with data meeting our inclusion criteria, excess mortality was estimated as observed mortality minus expected mortality. Third, to estimate excess mortality due to COVID-19 over the entire study period for all countries and territories in the analysis, and especially for locations without weekly or monthly all-cause mortality data, we developed a statistical model to directly predict the excess mortality due to COVID-19, using covariates that pertained to both the COVID-19 pandemic and background population health-related metrics at the population level before SARS-CoV-2 emerged. Fourth, we estimated excess mortality due to COVID-19, propagating uncertainty from each step. Further details on each of the analytical steps required to estimate COVID-19-related excess deaths are presented herein.</p>
<p>This study complies with the Guidelines for Accurate and Transparent Health Estimates Reporting 17 statement (appendix pp 3-4). Analyses were completed with
<rs xml:id="12965507" type="software">Stata</rs> (version
<rs xml:id="12965508" type="version" corresp="12965507">17</rs>), <rs xml:id="12965509" type="software">Python</rs> version (
<rs xml:id="12965510" type="version" corresp="12965509">3.7.7</rs>), and
<rs xml:id="12965511" type="software">R</rs> (version
<rs xml:id="12965512" type="version" corresp="12965511">4.0.3</rs>). Statistical
<rs xml:id="12970905" type="software" subtype="implicit">code</rs> used for these analyses can be found online. Results specific to the model run for this publication are accessible for each location online. The estimates viewable in our online <rs xml:id="12970906" type="software" subtype="implicit">tool</rs> will be iteratively updated as new data are incorporated and will ultimately supersede the results in this paper. The data used as inputs in these analyses are available for download on the Global Health Data Exchange website. These data include those available in public online repositories and those made available on request from the data provider. Data sources for reported COVID-19 mortality are also listed by location in the appendix (pp 8-37).
</p>
<p>All maps presented in this study were generated by the authors using
<rs xml:id="12965516" type="software" subtype="component" corresp="12965517">RStudio</rs> (<rs xml:id="12965517" type="software" subtype="environment">R</rs> version
<rs xml:id="12965518" type="version" corresp="12965517">4.0.3</rs>) and
<rs xml:id="12965519" type="software">ArcGIS Desktop</rs> (version
<rs xml:id="12965520" type="version" corresp="12965519">10.6.1</rs>), and no permissions were required to publish them.
</p>
<p>We searched government websites, compendia developed by the World Mortality Database, 18 the Human Mortality Database, and the European Statistical Office, and identified 74 countries and territories and an additional 266 subnational locations where either weekly or monthly all-cause mortality data were reported for periods in 2020 and 2021, and for up to 11 years previously (appendix pp 4-8, 47). These locations included 31 locations in low-income and middle-income countries. In addition to the time-detailed all-cause mortality data that are publicly available for the estimation of excess mortality, we also included empirical assessments of excess mortality for the nine provinces of South Africa (in addition to all-cause mortality data at the national level) and 12 states of India (in lieu of state-level all-cause mortality data). The Medical Research Council of South Africa used the data from both the civil registration system and the Rapid Mortality Surveillance Report to produce timely excess mortality estimates at the national and provincial levels (all nine provinces). For India, empirical assessment of excess mortality for 12 states used data from the civil registration system. For different months during the first and second waves of the COVID-19 epidemic in the 12 states in India, total numbers of deaths for those states during the corresponding months were made available (appendix pp 7-8). Using the mean reported deaths during the same periods in years 2018 and 2019, we were able to generate excess mortality rates for those Indian states after accounting for under-registration of mortality by the civil registration system at the state level.</p>
<p>We identified three types of data issues. First, all-cause mortality from weekly or monthly reporting often has considerable lags in reporting (appendix pp 51-84). Figure 1 shows the effect of lags in reporting of all-cause mortality on excess mortality for the vital registration system in the USA; it takes approximately 20 weeks for data in the USA to be nearly complete. We systematically reviewed input vital registration data and trimmed periods that were likely to be subject to late registration for all locations in the analysis. As these data have been made public only recently, we had limited information by which to identify the precise lag time in late registration; this was particularly true for locations where data are made available more sporadically and by month. We therefore took a conservative approach and excluded data from more recent weeks and months in 2021 in our calculation of excess mortality.</p>
<p>Second, in many European countries, registered deaths spiked in late July and early August (calendar weeks 31-33) of 2020, which was a period when reported COVID-19 deaths were extremely low as reported in our online <rs xml:id="12970907" type="software" subtype="implicit">tool</rs>. This period coincided with a heat wave; such spikes in all-cause mortality have been observed in Europe during similar timeframes in previous years. [19][20][21] Because our model cannot separate excess mortality due to COVID-19 from excess deaths occurring during a heat wave, we excluded these weeks of data for all countries in western Europe (classified according to the Global Burden of Diseases, Injuries, and Risk Factors Study [GBD] location groupings) from subsequent analyses to avoid potentially exaggerating the impact of COVID-19 on all-cause mortality during 2020. Late registration in all-cause mortality and its effect on computed excess mortality over time, USA Reported COVID-19 deaths (coloured lines) and estimated number of excess deaths due to the COVID-19 pandemic (dashed line) by week from series of weekly mortality data reported by calendar week from October, 2020, to February, 2022. The gap between the first calendar week during which mortality for a past week was reported and the subsequent reported levels indicates the gradual process by which completeness of reported deaths increases over time. Lines below 0 indicate reported deaths below the expected deaths value. Third, as under-reporting of deaths is common in most vital registration systems, especially those from outside the high-income group of countries, we corrected allcause mortality data for under-registration of death as estimated in GBD 2019; 22 six countries were corrected because GBD estimates suggested registration was less than 95% for the calendar year 2019. This under-reporting correction was in addition to, and distinct from, the late registration issue.</p>
<p>To estimate expected mortality, we developed six models, each fit separately by location. The first four models were based on first estimating the weekly (or monthly) seasonal pattern of mortality and then estimating the time trend in weekly or monthly mortality not explained by seasonality. We used a Bayesian spline to estimate the weekly seasonal pattern for each location using data from 2010, or the earliest year after 2010 when such data first became available, until around February, 2020, when the COVID-19 pandemic started for each location (appendix p 48). Second, using the same Bayesian spline, we estimated the time trend in the residuals (additional details provided in the appendix, pp 38-40). By combining the seasonal and secular trends, we generated predictions of the expected level of mortality in 2020 and 2021.</p>
<p>The specification of the spline can have a sizeable impact on the estimated expected mortality for a particular location. To make the results more robust to model specification, we included in our ensemble four variants according to where the second to last knot in the spline was placed: 6 months, 12 months, 18 months, and 24 months before the end of the period for the input data before the COVID-19 pandemic started for each location. We also included in the ensemble a Poisson model with fixed effects on week and year, and a model that assumed that expected mortality for 2020 and 2021 was the same as the corresponding weekly mortality observed in 2019. To derive weights for the different models in the ensemble, we assessed how each model performed in an out-of-sample predictive validity test. We fit the model to all data prior to March 1, 2019 and then evaluated how each model performed in predicting mortality between March, 2019, and February, 2020, compared with observed mortality in the same time period. We then weighted component models in the ensemble using 1 over the root mean squared error (RMSE) of the predictions for each component to down-weight component models with larger RMSE (and thus less accurate predictions) in the ensemble. A global weighting scheme was used for all locations. The distribution of RMSE by location for each of the six models included in the model ensemble and examples of the estimated excess mortality for each component model are provided in the appendix (p 49). Expected mortality from the ensemble model was subtracted from observed mortality in 2020 and 2021 to estimate excess mortality due to the COVID-19 pandemic.</p>
<p>Based on our estimation of expected mortality, and after applying the exclusions that account for late registration and other anomalies as previously described, we generated excess mortality estimates for each location where we had input data (figure 2). In addition, we added excess mortality estimates from two countries where the ensemble model could not be applied due to data constraints: South Africa (only the provinces) and India. We obtained national and province-level excess mortality All-age rate per 100 000 person-years rate estimates for South Africa which are regularly updated by the Medical Research Council of South Africa, and excess mortality estimates for select periods during the first and second waves of the COVID-19 epidemic for 12 states in India. Using these empirical excess mortality estimates, we developed a statistical model to predict excess mortality for all 191 national and 252 subnational locations in our analysis for the uniform period of Jan 1, 2020, to Dec 31, 2021 (appendix pp 40-43). This model was crucial for directly estimating excess mortality in countries where reported all-cause mortality data have not been available during the pandemic.</p>
<p>Various studies have examined the associations between particular underlying medical conditions and increased risk of severe COVID-19. We examined all available and relevant covariates on the basis of a meta-analysis conducted by the US Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 23 as well as covariates directly related to the COVID-19 pandemic, including seroprevalence (lagged by 25 days), mobility (lagged by 19 days), IDR (lagged by 19 days), and reported crude death rate due to COVID-19. For the model to be parsimonious, we used least absolute shrinkage and selection operator (LASSO) regression to help identify covariates that have sensible direction of effect on excess mortality rate (appendix pp 41-43). With the variable selection done via LASSO with input of mean level excess mortality and covariates, the following 15 covariates were included in our final log-linear model, where the dependent variable was excess mortality in logarithmic scale: lagged cumulative infection rate (seroprevalence) in log space, COVID-19 mortality rate in log space, crude death rate in log space, lagged IDR, annual inpatient admissions per capita, diabetes mortality rate in log space, HIV mortality rate in log space, lagged mobility, binned quality of vital registration data, average absolute latitude, cardiovascular disease mortality rate in log space, smoking prevalence, HAQ Index, proportion of the population aged 75 years or older, and universal health care coverage. These covariates explained 69•1% of the variation in the input data to this regression. We also calculated in-sample residuals for the locations that had directly observed excess mortality rates used in the regression (ie, India and South Africa). Regional and super-regional residuals, per the GBD regional classification system, were calculated as the mean residuals from locations included in each regional aggregate. We also calculated a countrylevel residual for India using the residual from the 12 states to recognise the dispersed periods and geographical regions covered by the civil registration data. Further details on the methodology are provided in the appendix (p 38-43). To validate our modelling process, we conducted out-of-sample predictive validity testing. Given the sparsity of input data on empirical excess mortality, we validated our model by repeatedly leaving one location out of the input data, then re-estimated the model and made predictions for the leftout location. Our analysis showed that the mean relative error of predicted excess mortality rate is 0•85% and the root mean squared error of predicted excess mortality rate is 0•00072, indicating a precise prediction model that has low bias.</p>
<p>In predicting excess mortality for all locations for the uniform period of Jan 1, 2020, to Dec 31, 2021, we used estimated coefficients and residuals from different aggregate levels together with all selected COVID-related covariates for the same period and other population health-related covariates for the year 2019 (appendix p 43). Ratios of estimated excess mortality to reported COVID-19 deaths were computed using the modelled excess mortality and the reported COVID-19 counts for each location.</p>
<p>As noted previously, policy makers and researchers have proposed many other causes of death that might have been affected by lockdown restrictions, unemployment, and increased poverty. To date, insufficient data are available to widely test for increases in deaths due to pandemic-related elements, such as deferred care, or for reductions in deaths, such as decreases in injury-related deaths due to reduced mobility.</p>
<p>To fully account for uncertainties in both the input empirical excess mortality and the selected covariates, 100 draws of excess mortality for each location were produced by use of 100 draws of coefficients of covariates and residuals and 100 draws of all selected covariates. Draw-level coefficients and residuals were obtained by repeating the excess mortality model 100 times with use of draw-level input excess mortality and covariates. Mean excess mortality with 95% uncertainty intervals [UIs] were generated on the basis of the draw-level estimates (appendix p 43).</p>
<p>Predicted excess mortality rates were used to compute the number of COVID-19-related excess deaths by multiplying the predicted excess mortality rate by person-years of exposure for the period. We used estimates of population size by location from the GBD, which by definition are the total person-years of exposure for a calendar year.</p>
<p>The funders of the study had no role in study design, data collection, data analysis, data interpretation, or the writing of the report. The table provides summary statistics for each country and territory, including reported deaths due to COVID-19, estimated excess deaths due to the COVID-19 pandemic, the ratio of the two, and reported and excess all-age COVID-19 mortality rates. The magnitude of the excess mortality burden has varied substantially between countries. The highest estimated excess mortality rate due to COVID-19 was 734•9 deaths (95% UI 594•1-879•2) per 100 000 of the population in Bolivia (compared with the global rate of 120•3 [113•1-129•3]), whereas negative excess mortality rates were estimated in Iceland, Australia, Singapore, New Zealand, and Taiwan (province of China), representing a large range. Excess mortality rates exceeded 300 deaths per 100 000 in 21 countries. At the regional level, the highest estimated excess mortality rates were in Andean Latin America, eastern Europe, central Europe, southern sub-Saharan Africa, and central Latin America, with several locations outside these ). These high-burden countries are distributed across all GBD regions of the world, reinforcing the evidence for the truly global nature of the pandemic. At the regional level, the number of excess deaths due to the COVID-19 pandemic was largest in the regions of south Asia, north Africa and the Middle East, and eastern Europe. We also computed the ratio of excess mortality rate to reported COVID-19 mortality rate as a measurement of undercounting of the true mortality impact of the pandemic. There were wide variations in the ratio across and within regions (figure 4; table). In high-income North America, the ratios were comparatively low, ranging from -0•05 to 4•41 between states in the USA, and from 1•05 to 5•59 between provinces in Canada. The ratio was 2•21 (95% UI 2•07-2•39) for central Latin America, with higher ratios in some countries including El Salvador (7•04 [5•49-8•57]) and lower ratios in others such as Costa Rica (0•85 [0•74-0•99]). Within Mexico, ratios were higher than 2•0 in ten states and ranged from 1•02 (0•90-1•15) in Colima to 4•90 (4•34-5•46) in Chiapas. In almost all national and subnational locations in southern and tropical Latin America, the ratios were lower than 2 and for some locations lower Based largely on empirical excess mortality observed in 12 Indian states, including during the surge in COVID-19 cases between April and July, 2021, we found that at the national level, India had an estimated 152•5 excess deaths (95% UI 138•6-163•3) per 100 000 of the population over the study period. This was much higher than its reported COVID-19 mortality rate of 18•3 per 100 000 over the same period. Heterogeneity in excess mortality among the 30 states of India was extremely high. From Jan 1, 2020, to Dec 31, 2021, eight Indian states had excess mortality rates higher than 200 per 100 000, a level only exceeded by 50 other countries in the world. These states were Uttarakhand, Manipur, Maharashtra, Chhattisgarh, Haryana, Himachal Pradesh, Punjab, and Karnataka. Conversely, Arunachal Pradesh, Telangana, Sikkim, Rajasthan, Gujarat, Uttar Pradesh, Jharkhand, West Bengal, and Goa had excess mortality rates that were lower than the global average of 120•6 per 100 000 (although 95% UIs overlap). Similarly, subnational heterogeneity was evident in the excess death counts. Seven states in India had excess deaths higher than 200 000 as of Dec 31, 2021. These were West Bengal (220 000 [132 000-254 000]), Madhya Pradesh (223 000 [188 000-253 000]), Tamil Nadu (260 000 [199 000-301 000]), Karnataka (284 000 [223 000-327 000]), Bihar (323 000 [257 000-388 000]), Uttar Pradesh (517 000 [418 000-602 000]), and Maharashtra (616 000 [484 000-736 000]). Although the excess mortality rates due to the COVID-19 pandemic among Indian states are not the highest in the world, because of India's large population, the country accounted for 22•3% (20•3-23•9) of global excess deaths as of Dec 31, 2021 (data not shown). Bihar, Uttar Pradesh, and Maharashtra had excess deaths higher than South Africa The magnitude of disease burden might have changed for many causes of death during the pandemic period due to both direct effects of lockdowns and the resulting economic turmoil. To correctly divide excess deaths into those directly due to SARS-CoV-2 infection and those associated with changes in other diseases and injuries, multiple drivers of change in mortality since the onset of the pandemic need to be considered. Unfortunately, to date only 36 countries have released 2020 cause of death data with detailed stratification by cause, to our knowledge. Although studies on specific populations in particular locations have been reported, we found insufficient statistical evidence to estimate these other changes in causes of death in a robust manner. Findings are mixed among the available evidence for alternative drivers of mortality that might have served to either increase or decrease excess mortality during the pandemic period. Some excess mortality might be attributable to reductions in health-care use across a number of causes; 14,15,24,25 however, the effect of reduced health-care use on health outcomes is difficult to prove. Many mechanisms have been proposed, including reduced vaccination rates 26 and reduced births in hospitals. 27,28 However, demonstrated increases in causespecific mortality from reduced health-care use do not have a generalised pattern in the countries with data released to date; the effect of changes in health-care use on excess mortality might also be greater in later years, rather than in 2020 or 2021. Even hypothesised decreases in injury-related deaths might be in doubt, as the US National Traffic and Safety Board has reported that road traffic deaths increased in 2020 in many US states despite decreases in transport mobility. 29 There is convincing evidence that rates of anxiety and depression increased during the pandemic period, which might lead to increases in deaths from suicide; 30,31 however, to date, evidence of increased suicide mortality is scarce apart from in Japan, where reported suicide deaths increased</p>
<p>during the pandemic. 32 Conversely, opioid deaths have increased in some US states and decreased in others compared with expected levels. [33][34][35][36] Deaths from some chronic conditions such as ischaemic heart disease or chronic respiratory disease decreased in particular months of 2020, 25 most notably in May and June in Europe; these decreases might have occurred because frail individuals who died from COVID-19 earlier in the year might otherwise have died from these chronic conditions. Supporting evidence for reductions in chronic conditions (particularly respiratory conditions) includes reductions in air pollution in the months of March and April in 2020, 37 but with the possible exception of India, 38 aggregated concentrations of air pollution during the entire pandemic period up to Dec 31, 2021 were only slightly lower than prepandemic concentrations. The most compelling evidence to date of a change in cause-specific mortality in the pandemic period is the decrease, especially in the Northern Hemisphere, in flu and respiratory syncytial virus (RSV) deaths seen in the months of January to March, 2021; decreases in cases of 80% or more have been reported to WHO. Given the scarce and inconsistent evidence of the effect the COVID-19 pandemic on cause-specific deaths, and the extremely scarce high-quality data on causes of death during the pandemic, our excess mortality estimates reflect the full impact of the pandemic on mortality around the world (after correcting for known biases), not just the deaths directly attributable to SARS-CoV-2 infection. As cause of death data for detailed causes are made available for 2020 for more countries in the future, we will be able to delineate the fraction of excess deaths due to SARS-CoV-2 infection versus indirect effects of the pandemic and responses to it. Separating the total number of deaths due to SARS-CoV-2 infection from excess mortality due to the pandemic will also be crucial for accurately estimating the infection-fatality ratio in every location, since that ratio requires the total number of deaths directly due to infection as an input.</p>
<p>Nonetheless, of the 12•3 million more excess deaths versus reported COVID-19 deaths, a substantial fraction of these will probably be shown to be from SARS-CoV-2 infection. This fraction, however, is likely to vary by location. For instance, in some high-income countries like Belgium and Sweden, which have used audits to investigate potential COVID-19-related deaths and have taken an inclusive approach to statistical reporting (available on the European Statistical Recovery Dashboard), 39 the ratio between excess deaths and reported COVID-19 deaths is close to 1. This outcome suggests that in some locations, the net change in mortality rates across other diseases and injuries during the pandemic period has been minimal. Conversely, audited cause of death data from both Russia and Mexico indicate that a substantial proportion of excess deaths could not be attributed to SARS-CoV-2 infection in these locations. Although these and other findings suggest that a higher fraction of excess deaths are likely due to SARS-CoV-2 infection in high-income countries than elsewhere, sufficient evidence on this topic is too sparse to make any conclusion for all countries. As increased data on the pandemic period are eventually made available, more sophisticated analyses will be possible to dissect the effects of different drivers in different locations.</p>
<p>The highest ratios of excess deaths to reported COVID-19 deaths were observed in parts of central Asia and most countries in sub-Saharan Africa (excluding southern sub-Saharan Africa). These high ratios are unlikely to be fully explained by dramatic increases in other causes of death during the pandemic and must at least partly be related to a paucity in extensive testing, medical practices, or state guidance on what should count as a death from COVID-19. Behavioural data, available in our online <rs xml:id="12970908" type="software" subtype="implicit">tool</rs>, suggest that in comparison with high-income countries including Canada, many states in the USA, and some countries in western Europe, mask use across these regions was generally much lower throughout the pandemic; mobility, measured via cell phone application use, was much higher; and many fewer social distancing mandates were put in place. Furthermore, our variable selection analysis found that in addition to pandemicrelated indicators such as IDR and mobility, background population health-related metrics such as HAQ Index, crude death rate, and inpatient admission rates are also predictive of excess mortality due to the COVID-19 pandemic. These factors might explain the large and under-reported COVID-19 epidemics in sub-Saharan Africa and central Asia, but more data are needed to fully understand the patterns in these regions. More attention should be given to locations like these, where dramatically low IDRs and rates of reported COVID-19 deaths have masked the true severity of the pandemic.</p>
<p>Weekly reporting of all-cause deaths has proven to be extremely useful in understanding the mortality impacts of the COVID-19 pandemic. Many countries have made a concerted effort to report data from vital registration in a much timelier manner than normal. Our analysis found that the lag between occurrence and registration of death varied substantially between countries, even between high-income countries with robust vital registration systems. Although such lags in reporting documented here show there are limitations to this rapid reporting in some countries such as the USA, these data have substantial value for epidemiological surveillance. Governments should try to use digital reporting of cause of death data and rapid release of the data to the public health community. If more countries invested in timely reporting, we would not only be able to track the effects of this pandemic and future pandemics, but we could more rapidly evaluate the effect of behavioural changes, such as social distancing, on mortality rates of other diseases and injuries. At the global level, our excess mortality estimates are very similar to those reported by The Economist, the only other source of COVID-19 excess mortality at a global scale for a similar time period. For a majority of the countries and territories covered by both analyses (104 of 187), the uncertainty intervals from this study and those from The Economist overlap, meaning no statistically significant difference between them. However, there are dramatic differences in the estimated excess mortality counts between the two studies for many countries (appendix p 50). The relative difference between the estimates from each study, defined as the ratio between excess deaths from The Economist study over those from our study minus 1, ranges from -382•7% (Vanuatu) to 2282•3% (China). In terms of absolute relative difference, at least a 25% difference is observed in 129 of 187 countries. Some 23 countries have absolute relative differences between the two studies of higher than 100%. For the 121 countries and territories for which both studies predict more than 5000 excess deaths, the estimates from The Economist tend to be lower than in this study. Although the global total produced by The Economist was similar at 18•0 million (95% UI 10•9-24•4) excess deaths, which is about 212 000 deaths fewer than the estimate derived in this study, country contributions to the totals varied. The Economist estimated 192 000 fewer excess deaths for Mexico, 140 000 for the USA, and 140 000 for Peru, and 1•07 million additional excess deaths for India, 409 000 for China, and 193 000 for Sudan. For sub-Saharan Africa, the absolute relative differences range from 0•6% in Gabon to 310•7% in Burundi. The absolute relative difference is at least 50% among 21 out of 46 countries in the region.</p>
<p>This study has a number of limitations. First, different modelling strategies, although closely related, were used for the estimation of excess mortality due to COVID-19 depending on the availability of time series data on allcause mortality before and during the pandemic. For countries without reporting of all-cause mortality by week or month, we used a statistical model to predict the COVID-19 excess mortality rate. Direct measurement would be preferable to modelled excess mortality estimates not based on all-cause mortality data, which are usually more robust, from the locations themselves. Second, we excluded from the assessment of excess mortality the most recent weeks and months in 2021 because of the evidence that late registration can take 20 weeks or longer to catch up. These exclusions help make our assessment closer to the true impact of COVID-19 for the period when data were kept in the analysis, improving the predictions made based on these input data for the entire modelled period. However, there is subjectivity to the exact limit on the intervals to be excluded because many countries have not provided weekly reports to formally evaluate late registration timing. Third, we estimated cumulative COVID-19 excess mortality rate, rather than estimating temporal excess mortality rate by week or month. This was intentional, as we found considerable lags in the reporting of COVID-19 death data compared with more precise data from vital statistics after allowing time for reporting of the day of death. In some cases, either allcause mortality or COVID-19 mortality is tabulated by time of registration, rather than time of occurrence. The disconnect between timing of these two data streams leads to unrealistic values when COVID-19 mortality rate, a key covariate in predicting excess mortality rate, is used to predict time-detailed excess mortality rate. Simple simulation studies that we conducted (not shown) showed that even 1-2-week differences in reporting lags between the sources could lead to large swings in the weekly ratios between excess mortality and reported COVID-19 mortality. For this reason, we believe that analysing the cumulative excess mortality is much more robust. Fourth, as studies from a few selected countries including the Netherlands and Sweden have suggested, 40 we suspect most of the excess mortality during the pandemic is from COVID-19. However, sufficient empirical evidence is absent in most countries. Given the high amount of heterogeneity in epidemiological profiles among countries, it is prudent not to make such strong assumptions before more research on this topic is done. Fifth, although our variable selection process produced 15 covariates that we included in our final model, inclusion of other variables might have improved our model predictions. Sixth, strict lockdown and mediation interventions can lead to negative excess mortality during the pandemic (ie, expected mortality is higher than observed all-cause mortality during the pandemic). We estimated that several countries, including Australia and New Zealand, have had negative excess mortality during the pandemic. This observation is probably due to decreases in mortality from diseases and injuries for which exposure to related risks has been reduced during the pandemic. In our prediction model for locations without timedetailed all-cause mortality before and during the pandemic, we did not attempt to predict negative excess mortality rates, as such evidence is not strong enough from a small number of locations to extrapolate to the whole world. Future studies are warranted to examine the effect of lockdown on changes in specific causes of death. Related to this decision not to predict negative excess mortality, our excess mortality estimates for the provinces in China were driven by covariates only. Although we recognise that similar, if not stricter, lockdown practices have been implemented in China compared with those we have seen in countries such as Australia and New Zealand, there is an absence of empirical information on vital registration data to make proper excess mortality estimates with the models we have developed. As more information becomes available in the near future, further improvements to our estimates are warranted. Seventh, various drivers</p>
<p>For The Economist COVID-19 excess death estimates see https://www.economist.com/ graphic-detail/coronavirusexcess-deaths-tracker are responsible for the changes in all-cause and cause-specific mortality in a population. Therefore, in estimating excess mortality due to COVID-19, the roles of confounders of changes in mortality during the pandemic should be resolved. We excluded mortality spikes in selected summer weeks in Europe that coincided with a heatwave, when the pandemic was at its lowest point in terms of transmission. However, scarcity of empirical evidence on other confounders and the information on cause-specific mortality that is associated with such confounders prevented us from further and more detailed data analysis. As the body of evidence grows in the future on both potential confounders and cause-specific mortality, such information should be incorporated into future iterations of the analysis presented in this study. Eighth, our excess mortality estimates are based on all-age mortality data, male and female data combined, from vital registration systems, and therefore cannot be disaggregated by age or sex. COVID-19 disproportionally affects older and fragile populations, and we should expect varying age patterns of excess mortality based on a population's demographic and epidemiological profiles. Unfortunately, weekly and monthly vital registration data by age and sex for 2020 and 2021 are currently too sparse (and tend to be in broad age groups when available) to robustly model excess mortality by age and sex, or to use to build models that predict this age pattern across countries with acceptable out-of-sample predictive validity. We intend to evaluate age-specific and sex-specific excess mortality in future iterations of this analysis when data disaggregated by age and sex become more widely available. Finally, the development and deployment of SARS-COV-2 vaccines have considerably lowered mortality rates among people who contract the virus and among the general population. As a result, we expect trends in excess mortality due to COVID-19 to change over time as the coverage of vaccination increases among populations and as new variants emerge. There will be great value in continuing to estimate excess mortality over time as these and other factors shift.</p>
<p>The full magnitude of the COVID-19 pandemic has been much greater in 2020 and 2021 than is indicated by reported deaths due to COVID-19, with COVID-19 potentially being a leading cause of mortality in 2020 and 2021. Further research and increased</p>
<p>https://www.cdc.gov/flu/ weekly/index.html</p>
<p>www.thelancet.com Published online March 10, 2022 https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02796-3</p>
<p>www.thelancet.com Published online March 10, 2022 https://doi.org/10.1016/S0140-6736(21)02796-3</p>
<p>Funding was provided by the Bill &amp; Melinda Gates Foundation, J Stanton, T Gillespie, and J and E Nordstrom. A J Ferrari is supported by a National Health and Medical Research Council Early Career Fellowship grant (APP1121516) and is employed by the Queensland Centre for Mental Health Research which receives core funding from the Queensland Department of Health. S Nomura would like to acknowledge the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology of Japan. R C Reiner Jr was partially supported by the National Science Foundation (award number FAIN: 2031096). A L P Ribeiro was partially supported by the Brazilian National Council for Scientific and Technological Development (grant numbers 310679/2016-8 and 465518/2014-1), by the Minas Gerais State Agency for Research and Development (grant numbers PPM-00428-17 and RED-00081-16), and Coordination for the Improvement of Higher Education Personnel (grant number 88887.507149/2020-00). D F Santomauro is employed by the Queensland Centre for Mental Health Research which receives core funding from the Queensland Department of Health. C S Wiysonge's work is supported by the South African Medical Research Council. Editorial note: the Lancet Group takes a neutral position with respect to territorial claims in published maps.</p>
<p>availability of cause of death data will be crucial for distinguishing the proportion of excess mortality that was</p>
<p>The data sources used in these analyses are available to download on the Global Health Data Exchange website. Reported COVID-19 death data sources are also listed by location and institution in the appendix (pp 8-37).</p>
</body>
</text>
</tei>