<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc xml:id="_1"/>
        <encodingDesc>
            <appInfo>
                <application version="0.8.1-SNAPSHOT" ident="GROBID" when="2024-06-24T16:12+0000">
                    <ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
                </application>
            </appInfo>
        </encodingDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text xml:lang="en">
<body>
        <p>The Concise Guide to PHARMACOLOGY 2015/16 provides concise overviews of the key properties of over 1750 human drug targets with their pharmacology, plus links to an open access knowledgebase of drug targets and their ligands (www.guidetopharmacology.org), which provides more detailed views of target and ligand properties. The full contents can be found at http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/ 10.1111/bph.13354/full. G protein-coupled receptors are one of the eight major pharmacological targets into which the Guide is divided, with the others being: G protein-coupled receptors, ligand-gated ion channels, voltage-gated ion channels, other ion channels, nuclear hormone receptors, catalytic receptors and transporters. These are presented with nomenclature guidance and summary information on the best available pharmacological tools, alongside key references and suggestions for further reading. The Concise Guide is published in landscape format in order to facilitate comparison of related targets. It is a condensed version of material contemporary to late 2015, which is presented in greater detail and constantly updated on the website www.guidetopharmacology.org, superseding data presented in the previous Guides to Receptors &amp; Channels and the Concise Guide to PHARMACOLOGY 2013/14. It is produced in conjunction with NC-IUPHAR and provides the official IUPHAR classification and nomenclature for human drug targets, where appropriate. It consolidates information previously curated and displayed separately in IUPHAR-DB and GRAC and provides a permanent, citable, point-in-time record that will survive database updates.</p>
        <p>monophosphatase only in the presence of high substrate concentrations. Some inhibitors are irreversible, including a group known as suicide substrates, which bind to the ligand recognition site and then couple covalently to the enzyme. It is beyond the scope of the Guide to give mechanistic information about the inhibitors described, although generally this information is avail-able from the indicated literature. Many enzymes require additional entities for functional activity. Some of these are used in the catalytic steps, while others promote a particular conformational change. Co-factors are tightly bound to the enzyme and include metal ions and heme groups. Co-enzymes are typically small molecules which accept or donate functional groups to assist in the enzymatic reaction. Examples include ATP, NAD, NADP and S-adenosylmethionine, as well as a number of vitamins, such as riboflavin (vitamin B1) and thiamine (vitamin B2). Where co-factors/co-enzymes have been identified, the Guide indicates their involvement.</p>
        <p>This is a complete listing of enzyme families included in the online IUPHAR/BPS Guide to PHARMACOLOGY database. Summary information is provided for a subset of enzyme families (those with page numbers) in the tables below. Family members judged to be of significant pharmacological interest have been included, with further enzymes listed in the database. G11 -) use the co-substrate ATP to phosphorylate serine and/or threonine residues on target proteins. Analysis of the human genome suggests the presence of 518 protein kinases in man, with over 100 protein kinase-like pseudo-genes [313]. It is beyond the scope of the Concise Guide to list all these protein kinase activities; the full listing may be seen at Inhibitors sotrastaurin (pIC 50 8.7) [506], GÖ 6983 (pIC 50 8.1) [183], GF109203X (pIC 50 7.8) [490] -Bovine, 7-hydroxystaurosporine (pIC 50 7.5) [431] GÖ 6983 (pIC 50 8.2) [183], 7-hydroxystaurosporine (pIC 50 7.5) [431] Selective inhibitors ruboxistaurin (pIC 50 8.2) [238], enzastaurin (pIC 50 7.5) [132], CGP53353 (pIC 50 6.4) [70] - [506], GÖ 6983 (pIC 50 8.1) [183], 7-hydroxystaurosporine (pIC 50 7.5) [431] sotrastaurin (pIC 50 8.9) [506], GÖ 6983 (pIC 50 8) [183] Eta subfamily Inhibitors ridaforolimus (pIC 50 9.7) [408], torin 1 (pIC 50 9.5) [291], INK-128 (pIC 50 9) [219], INK-128 (pK i 8.9) [219], gedatolisib (pIC 50 8.8) [500], dactolisib (pIC 50 8.2) [310], PP-242 (pIC 50 8.1) [14], PP121 (pIC 50 8) [14], XL388 (pIC 50 8) [472], PF-04691502 (pK i 7.8) [290], apitolisib (pK i 7.8) [467] Selective inhibitors everolimus (pIC 50 8.7) [427], temsirolimus (pIC 50 5.8) [266] Searchable Inhibitors R547 (pK i 9) [107], palbociclib (pIC 50 8) [151], Ro-0505124 (pIC 50 7.7) [115], riviciclib (pIC 50 7.</p>
        <p>2) [246], alvocidib (pK i 7.</p>
        <p>2) [64] palbociclib (pIC 50 7.8) [151] GSK subfamily 2) [407], LY2090314 (pIC 50 9) [125], CHIR-99021 (pIC 50 8.2) [407], SB 216763 (pIC 50 8.1) [88], 1-azakenpaullone (pIC 50 7.7) [272], SB-415286 (pIC 50 7.4) [88], IM-12 (pIC 50 7.3) [424] Selective inhibitors AZD2858 (pK i 8.3) [29] Comments Due to its Tau phosphorylating activity, small molecule inhibitors of GSK-3β are being investigated as potential treatments for Alzheimer's disease (AD) [29]. GSK-3β also plays a role in canonical Wnt pathway signalling, the normal activity of which is crucial for the maintenance of normal bone mass. It is hypothesised that small molecule inhibitors of GSK-3β may provide effective therapeutics for the treatment of diseases characterised by low bone mass [317]. Inhibitors trametinib (pIC 50 9-9.1) [173,536], PD 0325901 (pIC 50 8.1) [195], binimetinib (pIC 50 7.9) [382], refametinib (pIC 50 7.7) [229], CI-1040 (pK d 6.9) [105] trametinib (pIC 50 8.7) [536], binimetinib (pIC 50 7.9) [382], refametinib (pIC 50 7.</p>
        <p>3) [229] Searchable [191,395], filgotinib (pIC 50 8) [497] NS-018 (pIC 50 9.1) [350], BMS-911543 (pIC 50 9) [393], AT-9283 (pIC 50 8.9) [218], XL019 (pIC 50 8.7) [143], fedratinib (pIC 50 8.5) [311,521], gandotinib (pIC 50 8.4) [308] AT-9283 (pIC 50 9) [218] -Selective inhibitors -compound 1d (pIC 50 9) [509] --</p>
        <p>The JAK2 V617F mutation, which causes constitutive activation, plays an oncogenic role in the pathogenesis of the myeloproliferative disorders, polycythemia vera, essential thrombocythemia, and idiopathic myelofibrosis [58,109]. Small molecule compounds which inhibit aberrant JAK2 activity are being developed as novel anti-cancer pharmaceuticals.</p>
        <p>--</p>
        <p>Peptidases and proteinases AD: Aspartic (A) Peptidases A22: Presenilin Overview: Presenilin (PS)-1 or -2 act as the catalytic component/essential co-factor of the γ-secretase complex responsible for the final carboxy-terminal cleavage of amyloid precursor protein (APP) [249] in the generation of amyloid beta (Aβ) [6,471]. Given that the accumulation and aggregation of Aβ in the brain is pivotal in the development of Alzheimer's disease (AD), inhibition of PS activity is one mechanism being investigated as a therapeutic option for AD [177]. Several small molecule inhibitors of PS-1 have been investigated, with some reaching early clinical trials, but none have been formally approved. Dewji et al (2015) have reported that small peptide fragments of human PS-1 can significantly inhibit Aβ production (total Aβ, Aβ40 and Aβ42)</p>
        <p>both in vitro and when infused in to the brains of APP transgenic mice [111]. The most active small peptides in this report were P4 [PMID: 25923432] and P8 [PMID: 25923432], from the aminoterminal domain of PS-1.</p>
        <p>Peptidases and proteinases MA: Metallo (M) Peptidases M1: Aminopeptidase N Overview: Aminopeptidases catalyze the cleavage of amino acids from the amino (N) terminus of protein or peptide substrates, and are involved in many essential cellular functions. Members of this enzyme family may be monomeric or multi-subunit complexes, and many are zinc metalloenzymes [480]. Comment: folate hydrolase is also known as NAALADase as it is responsible for the hydrolysis of N-acetaspartylglutamate to form N-acetylaspartate and L-glutamate. In the gut, the enzyme assists in the assimilation of folate by hydrolysing dietary poly-gamma-glutamylfolate. The enzyme is highly expressed in the prostate, and its expression is up-regulated in cancerous tissue. A tagged version of the antibody capromab has been used for imaging purposes. Inhibitors nafamostat (pIC 50 4.9) [203] lepirudin (pK i 13) [511], desirudin (pK i 12.7) [242], AZ12971554 (pK i 9.5) [16], melagatran (pK i 8.7) [186], bivalirudin (pK i 8.6) [527], dabigatran (pK i 8.3) [198], argatroban (pK i 7.7) [225] rivaroxaban (pK i 9.4) [380], edoxaban (pK i 9.</p>
        <p>2) [385], apixaban (pK i 9.1) [528] alvelestat (pK i 8) [463], sivelestat (pIC 50 7.4) [96] Selective inhibitors -AR-H067637 (pIC 50 8.</p>
        <p>Enzymes Peptidases and proteinases PB: Threonine (T) Peptidases T1: Proteasome</p>
        <p>The T1 macropain beta subunits form the catalytic proteinase core of the 20S proteasome complex [86]. This catalytic core enables the degradation of peptides with Arg, Phe, Tyr, Leu, and Glu adjacent to the cleavage site. The β5 subunit is the principal target of the approved drug proteasome inhibitor bortezomib.</p>
        <p>Nomenclature proteasome (prosome, macropain) subunit, beta type, 5</p>
        <p>Overview: Acetylcholine is familiar as a neurotransmitter in the central nervous system and in the periphery. In the somatic nervous system, it activates nicotinic acetylcholine receptors at the skeletal neuromuscular junction. It is also employed in the autonomic nervous system, in both parasympathetic and sympathetic branches; in the former, at the smooth muscle neuromuscu-lar junction, activating muscarinic acetylcholine receptors. In the latter, acetylcholine is involved as a neurotransmitter at the ganglion, activating nicotinic acetylcholine receptors. Acetylcholine is synthesised in neurones through the action of choline Oacetyltransferase and metabolised after release through the extracellular action of acetylcholinesterase and cholinesterase. Choline is accumulated from the extracellular medium by selective transporters (see SLC5A7 and the SLC44 family). Acetylcholine is accumulated in synaptic vesicles through the action of the vesicular acetylcholine transporter SLC18A3. Comments Splice variants of choline O-acetyltransferase are suggested to be differentially distributed in the periphery and CNS (see [28]).</p>
        <p>--</p>
        <p>A number of organophosphorus compounds inhibit acetylcholinesterase and cholinesterase irreversibly, including pesticides such as chlorpyrifos-oxon, and nerve agents such as tabun, soman and sarin. AChE is unusual in its exceptionally high turnover rate which has been calculated at 740 000/min/molecule [505].</p>
        <p>Overview: A multifunctional, ubiquitous molecule, adenosine acts at cell-surface G protein-coupled receptors, as well as numerous enzymes, including protein kinases and adenylyl cyclase. Extracellular adenosine is thought to be produced either by export or by metabolism, predominantly through ecto-5'-nucleotidase activity (also producing inorganic phosphate). It is inactivated either by extracellular metabolism via adenosine deaminase (also producing ammonia) or, following uptake by nucleoside trans-porters, via adenosine deaminase or adenosine kinase (requiring ATP as co-substrate). Intracellular adenosine may be produced by cytosolic 5'-nucleotidases or through S-adenosylhomocysteine hydrolase (also producing L-homocysteine). Comments: An extracellular adenosine deaminase activity, termed ADA2 or adenosine deaminase growth factor (ADGF, CECR1, Q9NZK5) has been identified [94,309], which is insensitive to EHNA [546]. Other forms of adenosine deaminase act on ribonucleic acids and may be divided into two families: ADAT1 (Q9BUB4) deaminates transfer RNA; ADAR (EC 3.5.4.37, also known as 136 kDa double-stranded RNA-binding protein, P136, K88DSRBP, Interferon-inducible protein 4); ADARB1 (EC 3.5.-.-, , also known as dsRNA adenosine deaminase) and ADARB2 (EC 3.5.-.-, also known as dsRNA adenosine deaminase B2, RNA-dependent adenosine deaminase 3) act on double-stranded RNA. Particular polymorphisms of the ADA gene result in loss-of-function and se-vere combined immunodeficiency syndrome. Adenosine deaminase is able to complex with dipeptidyl peptidase IV (EC 3.4.14.5, DPP4, also known as T-cell activation antigen CD26, TP103, adenosine deaminase complexing protein 2) to form a cell-surface activity [248].</p>
        <p>Protein kinase A-mediated phosphorylation (Rat) [1] Protein kinase A-mediated phosphorylation [239] Protein kinase A-mediated phosphorylation [240] Protein kinase A-mediated phosphorylation [240] Endogenous substrates</p>
        <p>Enzymes L-Arginine turnover Overview: L-arginine is a basic amino acid with a guanidino sidechain. As an amino acid, metabolism of L-arginine to form L-ornithine, catalysed by arginase, forms the last step of the urea production cycle. L-Ornithine may be utilised as a precursor of polyamines (see Carboxylases and Decarboxylases) or recycled via L-argininosuccinic acid to L-arginine. L-Arginine may itself be decarboxylated to form agmatine, although the prominence of this pathway in human tissues is uncertain. L-Arginine may be used as a precursor for guanidoacetic acid formation in the creatine synthesis pathway under the influence of arginine:glycine amidinotransferase with L-ornithine as a byproduct. Nitric oxide synthase uses L-arginine to generate nitric oxide, with L-citrulline also as a byproduct. L-Arginine in proteins may be subject to post-translational mod- Overview: Arginase (EC 3.5.3.1) are manganese-containing isoforms, which appear to show differential distribution, where the ARG1 isoform predominates in the liver and erythrocytes, while ARG2 is associated more with the kidney.</p>
        <p>Comments: N -hydroxyarginine, an intermediate in NOS metabolism of L-arginine acts as a weak inhibitor and may function as a physiological regulator of arginase activity. Although isoform-selective inhibitors of arginase are not available, examples of inhibitors selective for arginase compared to NOS are N -hydroxy-nor-L-arginine [483], S-(2-boronoethyl)-L-cysteine [90,256] and 2(S)-amino-6-boronohexanoic ac [22,90]. 3) [169], NIL (pIC 50 5.5) [341], aminoguanidine [92] 3-bromo-7NI (pIC 50 6.1-6.5) [40], 7NI (pIC 50 5.3) [19] Comments: The reductase domain of NOS catalyses the reduction of cytochrome c and other redox-active dyes [322]. NADPH:O 2 oxidoreductase catalyses the formation of superoxide anion/H 2 O 2 in the absence of L-arginine and sapropterin. The activity of ODC is regulated by the presence of an antizyme (ENSG00000104904) and an ODC antizyme inhibitor (ENSG00000155096).</p>
        <p>S-allylglycine is also an inhibitor of SAMDC [368].</p>
        <p>Bale</p>
        <p>Overview: Catecholamines are defined by the presence of two adjacent hydroxyls on a benzene ring with a sidechain containing an amine. The predominant catacholamines in mammalian biology are the neurotransmitter/hormones dopamine, (-)-noradrenaline (norepinephrine) and (-)-adrenaline (epinephrine).</p>
        <p>These hormone/transmitters are synthesized by sequential metabolism from L-phenylalanine via L-tyrosine. Hydroxylation of L-tyrosine generates levodopa, which is decarboxylated to form dopamine. Hydroxylation of the ethylamine sidechain generates (-)-noradrenaline (norepinephrine), which can be methylated to form (-)-adrenaline (epinephrine). In particular neuronal and adrenal chromaffin cells, the catecholamines dopamine, (-)-noradrenaline and (-)-adrenaline are accumulated into vesicles under the influence of the vesicular monoamine transporters (VMAT1/SLC18A1 and VMAT2/SLC18A2). After release into the synapse or the blood-stream, catecholamines are accumulated through the action cell-surface transporters, primarily the dopamine (DAT/SLC6A3) and norepinephrine transporter (NET/SLC6A2). The primary routes of metabolism of these catecholamines are oxidation via monoamine oxidase activities of methylation via catechol Omethyltransferase.</p>
        <p>Overview: The functional enzyme is a heterodimer of SPT1 (LCB1) with either SPT2 (LCB2) or SPT3 (LCB2B); the small subunits of SPT (ssSPTa or ssSPTb) bind to the heterodimer to enhance enzymatic activity. The complexes of SPT1/SPT2/ssSPTa and SPT1/SPT2/ssSPTb were most active with palmitoylCoA as substrate, with the latter complex also showing some activity with stearoylCoA [190]. Complexes involving SPT3 appeared more broad in substrate selectivity, with incorporation of myristoylCoA prominent for SPT1/SPT3/ssSPTa complexes, while SP1/SPT3/ssSPTb complexes had similar activity with C16, C18 and C20 acylCoAs [190].</p>
        <p>Ceramide turnover Acid ceramidase</p>
        <p>The six human ceramidases may be divided on the basis of pH optimae into acid, neutral and alkaline ceramidases, which also differ in their subcellular location.</p>
        <p>This lysosomal enzyme is proteolysed to form the mature protein made up of two chains from the same gene product [261].</p>
        <p>Overview: The six human ceramidases may be divided on the basis of pH optimae into acid, neutral and alkaline ceramidases, which also differ in their subcellular location.</p>
        <p>The enzyme is associated with the plasma membrane [475].</p>
        <p>-</p>
        <p>Comments: ASAH2B appears to be an enzymatically inactive protein, which may result from gene duplication and truncation.</p>
        <p>Ceramide turnover Alkaline ceramidases</p>
        <p>The six human ceramidases may be divided on the basis of pH optimae into acid, neutral and alkaline ceramidases, which also differ in their subcellular location.</p>
        <p>ACER1 is associated with the ER [466]. ACER2 is associated with the Golgi apparatus [534].</p>
        <p>ACER3 is associated with the ER and Golgi apparatus [314]. Comments: A ceramide kinase-like protein has been identified in the human genome (CERKL, Q49MI3).</p>
        <p>Castro</p>
        <p>Chromatin modifying enzymes</p>
        <p>Chromatin modifying enzymes, and other chromatin-modifying proteins, fall into three broad categories: writers, readers and erasers. The function of these proteins is to dynamically maintain cell identity and regulate processes such as differentiation, development, proliferation and genome integrity via recognition of specific 'marks' (covalent post-translational modifications) on histone proteins and DNA [267]. In normal cells, tissues and organs, precise co-ordination of these proteins ensures expression of only those genes required to specify phenotype or which are required at specific times, for specific functions. Chromatin modifications allow DNA modifications not coded by the DNA sequence to be passed on through the genome and underlies heritable phenomena such as X chromosome inactivation, aging, heterochromatin formation, reprogramming, and gene silencing (epigenetic control). To date at least eight distinct types of modifications are found on histones. These include small covalent modifications such as acetylation, methylation, and phosphorylation, the attachment of larger modifiers such as ubiquitination or sumoylation, and ADP ribosylation, proline isomerization and deimination. Chromatin modifications and the functions they regulate in cells are reviewed by Kouzarides (2007) [267]. Writer proteins include the histone methyltransferases, histone acetyltransferases, some kinases and ubiquitin ligases. Readers include proteins which contain methyl-lysinerecognition motifs such as bromodomains, chromodomains, tudor domains, PHD zinc fingers, PWWP domains and MBT domains. Erasers include the histone demethylases and histone deacetylases (HDACs and sirtuins). Dysregulated epigenetic control can be associated with human diseases such as cancer [129], where a wide variety of cellular and pro-tein abberations are known to perturb chromatin structure, gene transcription and ultimately cellular pathways [24,439]. Due to the reversible nature of epigenetic modifications, chromatin regulators are very tractable targets for drug discovery and the development of novel therapeutics. Indeed, small molecule inhibitors of writers (e.g. azacitidine and decitabine target the DNA methyltransferases DNMT1 and DNMT3 for the treatment of myelodysplastic syndromes [165,520]) and erasers (e.g. the HDAC inhibitors vorinostat, romidepsin and belinostat for the treatment of T-cell lymphomas [144,254]) are already being used in the clinic. The search for the next generation of compounds with improved specificity against chromatin-associated proteins is an area of intense basic and clinical research [56]. Current progress in this field is reviewed by Simó-Riudalbas and Esteller (2015) [440]. They generate both mono-methylated and dimethylated products; these may be symmetric (SDMA) or asym-metric (N G ,N G -dimethyl-L-arginine) versions, where both guanidine nitrogens are monomethylated or one of the two is dimethylated, respectively. Classes I, II and IV use Zn + as a co-factor, whereas catalysis by Class III enzymes requires NAD + as a co-factor, and members of this subfamily have ADP-ribosylase activity in addition to protein deacetylase function [420].</p>
        <p>HDACs have more general protein deacetylase activity, being able to deacetylate lysine residues in non-histone proteins [82] such as microtubules [221], the hsp90 chaperone [268] and the tumour suppressor p53 [302].</p>
        <p>Dysregulated HDAC activity has been identified in cancer cells and tumour tissues [288,410], making HDACs attractive molecular targets in the search for novel mechanisms to treat cancer [522].</p>
        <p>Several small molecule HDAC inhibitors are already approved for clinical use: romidepsin, belinostat, vorinostat, panobinostat, belinostat, valproic acid and chidamide. HDACs and HDAC inhibitors currently in development as potential anti-cancer therapeutics are reviewed by Simó-Riudalbas and Esteller (2015) [440].</p>
        <p>Cyclic nucleotide turnover Overview: Cyclic nucleotides are second messengers generated by cyclase enzymes from precursor triphosphates and hydrolysed by phosphodiesterases. The cellular actions of these cyclic nucleotides are mediated through activation of protein kinases (cAMP-and cGMP-dependent protein kinases), ion channels (cyclic nucleotide-gated, CNG, and hyperpolarization and cyclic nucleotide-gated, HCN) and guanine nucleotide exchange factors (GEFs, Epac). --Ca 2+ /calcineurin [376] Comments: Nitric oxide has been proposed to inhibit AC5 and AC6 selectively [210], although it is unclear whether this phenomenon is of physiological significance. A soluble adenylyl cyclase has been described (ADCY10, Q96PN6 [48]), unaffected by either Gα or Gβγ subunits, which has been suggested to be a cytoplasmic bicarbonate (pH-insensitive) sensor [75]. It can be inhibited selectively by KH7 (pIC 50 5.0-5.5) [208].</p>
        <p>Overview: Soluble guanylyl cyclase (GTP diphosphate-lyase (cyclising)), E.C. 4.6.1.2, is a heterodimer comprising α and β chains, both of which have two subtypes in man (predominantly α1β1; [544]).</p>
        <p>A haem group is associated with the β chain and is the target for the endogenous ligand nitric oxide (NO¯), and, potentially, carbon monoxide [150]. The enzyme converts guanosine-5'-triphosphate to the intracellular second messenger 3',5'-guanosine monophosphate (cyclic GMP). Selective activators BAY412272 [460], NO, YC1 [150], ataciguat [421], cinaciguat [461], riociguat [461] Inhibitors NS 2028 (pIC 50 8. Comments: ODQ also shows activity at other haem-containing proteins [134], while YC1 may also inhibit cGMP-hydrolysing phosphodiesterases [149,159].</p>
        <p>Enzymes Cyclic nucleotide turnover Exchange protein activated by cyclic AMP (Epac)</p>
        <p>Overview: Epacs are members of a family of guanine nucleotide exchange factors (ENSFM00250000000899), which also includes RapGEF5 (GFR, KIAA0277, MR-GEF, Q92565) and RapGEFL1 (Link-GEFII, Q9UHV5). They are activated endoge-nously by cyclic AMP and with some pharmacological selectivity by Once activated, Epacs induce an enhanced activity of the monomeric G proteins, Rap1 and Rap2 by facilitating binding of guanosine-5'-triphosphate in place of guanosine 5'-diphosphate, leading to activation of phospholipase C [423]. Substrates atorvastatin [140], codeine [140], diazepam [140], tamoxifen [140], erlotinib [140] Searchable Responsible for -hydroxylation of LTB 4 , LXB 4 [335], and tocopherols, including vitamin E [453] Responsible for -hydroxylation of LTB 4 , LXB 4 [335], and polyunsaturated fatty acids [135,194] Converts PGH 2 to 19-hydroxyPGH 2 [54]</p>
        <p>Converts arachidonic acid to 16-HETE and 18-HETE [353].</p>
        <p>Converts myristic acid to 14-hydroxymyristic acid [348].</p>
        <p>Converts anandamide to 14,15-epoxyeicosatrienoic ethanolamide [459].</p>
        <p>Converts</p>
        <p>Inhibited by dazoxiben [398] and camonagrel [182].</p>
        <p>Converts PGH 2 to PGI 2 [196]. Inhibited by tranylcypromine [181] Converts cholesterol to 7α-hydroxycholesterol [354].</p>
        <p>Converts dehydroepiandrosterone to 7α-DHEA [411].</p>
        <p>Converts 7α-hydroxycholest-4-en-3-one to 7-alpha,12α-dihydroxycholest-4-en-3-one (in rabbit) [226] in the biosynthesis of bile acids.</p>
        <p>Endocannabinoid turnover</p>
        <p>The principle endocannabinoids are 2-arachidonoylglycerol (2AG) and anandamide (Narachidonoylethanolamine, AEA), thought to be generated on demand rather than stored, although this may not always be the case [10]. Mechanisms for release and re-uptake of endocannabinoids (and related entities) are unclear, although candidates for intracellular transport have been suggested. For the generation of 2-arachidonoylglycerol, the key enzyme in-volved is diacylglycerol lipase (DGL), whilst several routes for anandamide synthesis have been described, the best characterized of which involves N-acylphosphatidylethanolaminephospholipase D (NAPE-PLD, [438]). Inactivation of these endocannabinoids appears to occur predominantly through monoacylglycerol lipase (MGL) and fatty acid amide hydrolase (FAAH) for 2-arachidonoylglycerol and anandamide, respectively. Note that these enzymes also contribute to the turnover of many endogenous ligands inactive at CB 1 and CB 2 cannabinoid receptors, such as N-oleoylethanolamide, N-palmitoylethanolamine and 2-oleoyl glycerol. In vitro experiments indicate that the endocannabinoids are also substrates for oxidative metabolism via cyclooxygenase, lipoxygenase and cytochrome P450 enzyme activities [9,145,450]. [171] anandamide oleamide N-oleoylethanolamide N-palmitoylethanolamine [518] oleamide N-oleoylethanolamide anandamide N-palmitoylethanolamine [518] N-palmitoylethanolamine MEA SEA N-oleoylethanolamide anandamide [495] Searchable Comments: Many of the compounds described as inhibitors are irreversible and so potency estimates will vary with incubation time. FAAH2 is not found in rodents [518] and few of the inhibitors described have been assessed at this enzyme activity.</p>
        <p>2-arachidonoylglycerol has been reported to be hydrolysed by multiple enzyme activities from neural preparations, including ABHD6 (Q9BV23) [41], ABHD12 (8N2K0) [41], neuropathy target esterase (PNPLA6, Q8IY17 [316]) and carboxylesterase 1 (CES1, P23141 [533]). Although these have been incompletely defined, WWL70 has been described to inhibit ABHD6 selectively with a pIC 50 value of 7.2 [284]. Other selective inhibitors of NAAA (with respect to FAAH) have been described, but these are not yet commercially available.</p>
        <p>Blankman</p>
        <p>Overview: Eicosanoids are 20-carbon fatty acids, where the usual focus is the polyunsaturated analogue arachidonic acid and its metabolites. Arachidonic acid is thought primarily to derive from phospholipase A2 action on membrane phosphatidylcholine, and may be re-cycled to form phospholipid through con-jugation with coenzyme A and subsequently glycerol derivatives. Oxidative metabolism of arachidonic acid is conducted through three major enzymatic routes: cyclooxygenases; lipoxygenases and cytochrome P450-like epoxygenases, particularly CYP2J2. Isoprostanes are structural analogues of the prostanoids (hence the nomenclature D-, E-, F-isoprostanes and isothromboxanes), which are produced in the presence of elevated free radicals in a nonenzymatic manner, leading to suggestions for their use as biomarkers of oxidative stress. Molecular targets for their action have yet to be defined. flurbiprofen (pIC 50 7.1) [512], fenoprofen (pIC 50 6.8) [17], ketoprofen (pIC 50 6.5) [55], suprofen (pIC 50 6.2) [55],</p>
        <p>benzquinamide (pIC 50 8.3) [17], flurbiprofen (pIC 50 8) [25], meclofenamic acid (pIC 50 7.4) [247], carprofen (pIC 50 7) [209], ketorolac (pIC 50 6.9) [503], nimesulide (pIC 50 6.2) [366], ketoprofen (pIC 50 6.</p>
        <p>2) [55],</p>
        <p>Selective inhibitors ketorolac (pIC 50 9.7) [512], FR122047 (pIC 50 7.5) [357] celecoxib (pIC 50 8.7) [38], valdecoxib (pIC 50 8.3) [473], diclofenac (pIC 50 7.7) [42], rofecoxib (pIC 50 6.1-6.5) [512], lumiracoxib (pK i 6.5) [43], meloxicam (pIC 50 6.3) [280], etoricoxib (pIC 50 6) [406] Prostaglandin synthases</p>
        <p>Overview: The lipoxygenases (LOXs) are a structurally related family of non-heme iron dioxygenases that function in the production, and in some cases metabolism, of fatty acid hydroperoxides. For arachidonic acid as substrate, these products are hydroperoxyeicosatetraenoic acids (HPETEs). In humans there are five lipoxygenases, the 5S-(arachidonate : oxygen 5-oxidoreductase), 12R-(arachidonate 12-lipoxygenase, 12R-type), 12S-(arachidonate : oxygen 12-oxidoreductase), and two distinct 15S-(arachidonate : oxygen 15-oxidoreductase) LOXs that oxygenate arachidonic acid in different positions along the carbon chain and form the corresponding 5S-, 12S-, 12R-, or 15S-hydroperoxides, respectively.</p>
        <p>Comments FLAP activity can be inhibited by MK-886 [116] and BAY-X1005 [197] leading to a selective inhibition of 5-LOX activity ----E-LOX metabolises the product from the 12R-lipoxygenase (12R-HPETE) to a specific epoxyalcohol compound [543].</p>
        <p>Comments: An 8-LOX (EC 1.13.11.40, arachidonate:oxygen 8-oxidoreductase) may be the mouse orthologue of 15-LOX-2 [158]. Some general LOX inhibitors are nordihydroguiaretic acid and esculetin. Zileuton and caffeic acid are used as 5-lipoxygenase inhibitors, while baicalein and CDC are 12-lipoxygenase inhibitors. The specificity of these inhibitors has not been rigorously assessed with all LOX forms: baicalein, along with other flavonoids, such as fisetin and luteolin, also inhibits 15-LOX-1 [414].</p>
        <p>Eicosanoid turnover Leukotriene and lipoxin metabolism Overview: Leukotriene A 4 (LTA 4 produced by 5-LOX activity, and lipoxins may be subject to further oxidative metabolism; -hydroxylation is mediated by CYP4F2 and CYP4F3, while βoxidation in mitochondria and peroxisomes proceeds in a manner dependent on coenzyme A conjugation. Conjugation of LTA 4 at the 6 position with reduced glutathione to generate LTC 4 occurs under the influence of leukotriene C 4 synthase, with the subsequent formation of LTD 4 and LTE 4 , all three of which are agonists at CysLT receptors. LTD 4 formation is catalysed by γglutamyltransferase, and subsequently dipeptidase 2 removes the terminal glycine from LTD 4 to generate LTE 4 . Leukotriene A 4 hydrolase converts the 5,6-epoxide LTA 4 to the 5-hydroxylated LTB 4 , an agonist for BLT receptors. LTA 4 is also acted upon by 12S-LOX to produce the trihydroxyeicosatetraenoic acids lipoxins LXA 4 and LXB 4 . Treatment with a LTA 4 hydrolase inhibitor in a murine model of allergic airway inflammation increased LXA 4 levels, in addition to reducing LTB 4 , in lung lavage fluid [400]. LTA 4 hydrolase is also involved in biosynthesis of resolvin Es. Aspirin has been reported to increase endogenous formation of 18S-hydroxyeicosapentaenoate (18S-HEPE) compared with 18R-HEPE, a resolvin precursor. Both enantiomers may be metabolised by human recombinant 5-LOX; recombinant LTA 4 hydrolase converted chiral 5S(6)-epoxide-containing intermediates to resolvin E1 and 18S-resolvin E1 [358].</p>
        <p>Enzymes GABA turnover</p>
        <p>The inhibitory neurotransmitter γ-aminobutyrate (GABA, 4-aminobutyrate) is generated in neurones by glutamic acid decarboxylase. GAD1 and GAD2 are differentially expressed during development, where GAD2 is thought to subserve a trophic role in early life and is distributed throughout the cytoplasm. GAD1 is expressed in later life and is more associated with nerve terminals [128] where GABA is principally accumulated in vesicles through the action of the vesicular inhibitory amino acid transporter SLC32A1. The role of γ-aminobutyraldehyde dehydrogenase (ALDH9A1) in neurotransmitter GABA synthesis is less clear. Following release from neurons, GABA may interact with either GABA A or GABA B receptors and may be accumu-lated in neurones and glia through the action of members of the SLC6 family of transporters. Successive metabolism through GABA transaminase and succinate semialdehyde dehydrogenase generates succinic acid, which may be further metabolized in the mitochondria in the tricarboxylic acid cycle.</p>
        <p>Overview: Phospholipids are the basic barrier components of membranes in eukaryotic cells divided into glycerophospholipids (phosphatidic acid, phosphatidylethanolamine, phosphatidylcholine, phosphatidylserine, phosphatidylinositol and its phosphorylated derivatives) and sphingolipids (ceramide phosphorylcholine and ceramide phosphorylethanolamine).</p>
        <p>Phosphatidylinositol may be phosphorylated at either 3-or 4-positions on the inositol ring by PI 3-kinases or PI 4-kinases, respectively. Phosphatidylinositol 3-kinases Phosphatidylinositol 3-kinases (PI3K, provisional nomenclature) catalyse the introduction of a phosphate into the 3-position of phosphatidylinositol (PI), phosphatidylinositol 4-phosphate (PIP) or phosphatidylinositol 4,5-bisphosphate (PIP 2 ). There is evidence that PI3K can also phosphorylate serine/threonine residues on proteins. In addition to the classes described below, further serine/threonine protein kinases, including ATM (Q13315) and mTOR (P42345), have been described to phosphorylate phosphatidylinositol and have been termed PI3Krelated kinases. Endogenous activation -PKD-mediated phosphorylation [199] (Sub)family-selective inhibitors wortmannin (pIC 50 6.7-6.8) [170,329] wortmannin (pIC 50 6.7-6.8) [170,329] Selective inhibitors -PIK-93 [259] Phosphatidylinositol-4-phosphate 3-kinase family the major physiological form of regulation of PLC-AE activity. PLC has been suggested to be activated non-selectively by the small molecule m3M3FBS [21], although this mechanism of action has been questioned [271]. The aminosteroid U73122 has been described as an inhibitor of phosphoinositide-specific PLC [447], although its selectivity among the isoforms is untested and it has been reported to occupy the H1 histamine receptor [222].</p>
        <p>Endogenous activators Gαq, Gα11, Gβγ [207,374,449] Gα16, Gβγ, Rac2 (RAC2, P15153) [59,223,224,281,374] Gαq, Gβγ [65,281,374] Gαq [237] PIP 3 [20] PIP 3 , Rac1 (RAC1, P63000), Rac2 (RAC2, P15153), Rac3 (RAC3, P60763) [20, 384,</p>
        <p>The sequence of PLA 2 -2C suggests a lack of catalytic activity, while PLA 2 -12B (GXIIB, GXIII sPLA 2 -like) appears to be catalytically inactive [413]. A further fragment has been identified with sequence similarities to Group II PLA 2 members. Otoconin 90 (OC90) shows sequence homology to PLA 2 -G10.</p>
        <p>A binding protein for secretory phospholipase A 2 has been identified which shows modest selectivity for sPLA 2 -1B over sPLA 2 -2A, and also binds snake toxin phospholipase A 2 [12]. The binding protein appears to have clearance function for circulating secretory phospholipase A 2 , as well as signalling functions, and is a candidate antigen for idiopathic membraneous nephropathy [27]. PLA 2 -G7 and PAFAH2 also express platelet-activating factor acetylhydrolase activity (EC 3.1.1.47).</p>
        <p>Enzymes Glycerophospholipid turnover phospholipase D</p>
        <p>Overview: Phosphatidylcholine-specific phospholipase D (PLD, EC 3.1.1.4) catalyses the formation of phosphatidic acid from phosphatidylcholine. In addition, the enzyme can make use of alcohols, such as butanol in a transphosphatidylation reaction [399].</p>
        <p>Endogenous activators ADP-ribosylation factor 1 (ARF1, P84077), PIP 2 , RhoA, PKC evoked phosphorylation, RalA [189,303] -Endogenous inhibitor Gβγ [391] Gβγ [391] Endogenous activators -ADP-ribosylation factor 1 (ARF1, P84077), PIP 2 [298], oleic acid [418] Selective inhibitors -VU0364739 (pIC 50 7.7) [279] Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Phosphatidylcholine-specific phospholipase D 6089 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.13354/full</p>
        <p>A lysophospholipase D activity (ENPP2, Q13822, also known as ectonucleotide pyrophosphatase/phosphodiesterase 2, phosphodiesterase I, nucleotide pyrophosphatase 2, autotaxin) has been described, which not only catalyses the production of lysophosphatidic acid (LPA) from lysophosphatidylcholine, but also cleaves ATP (see Goding et al., 2003 [175]). Additionally, an N-acylethanolaminespecific phospholipase D (NAPEPLD, Q6IQ20) has been char-acterized, which appears to have a role in the generation of endocannabinoids/endovanilloids, including anandamide [362]. This enzyme activity appears to be enhanced by polyamines in the physiological range [292] and fails to transphosphatidylate with alcohols [381]. Three further, less well-characterised isoforms are PLD3 (PLD3, Q8IV08, other names Choline phosphatase 3, HindIII K4L homolog, Hu-K4), PLD4 (PLD4, Q96BZ4, other names Choline phosphatase 4, Phosphatidylcholine-hydrolyzing phospholipase, D4C14orf175 UNQ2488/PRO5775) and PLD5 (PLD5, Q8N7P1). PLD3 has been reported to be involved in myogenesis [365]. PLD4 is described not to have phospholipase D catalytic activity [539], but has been associated with inflammatory disorders [360,468,484]. Sequence analysis suggests that PLD5 is catalytically inactive.</p>
        <p>Hydrogen sulphide synthesis Overview: Hydrogen sulfide is a putative gasotransmitter, with similarities to nitric oxide and carbon monoxide. Although the enzymes indicated have multiple enzymatic activities, the focus here is the generation of hydrogen sulphide and the enzymatic characteristics are described accordingly. Cystathionine β-synthase and cystathionine γ-lyase are pyridoxal phosphate-dependent enzymes, while 3-mercaptopyruvate sulfurtransferase functions as a pyridoxal phosphate-independent pathway.</p>
        <p>Overview: Listed in this section are hydrolases not accumulated in other parts of the Concise Guide, such as monoacylglycerol lipase and acetylcholinesterase. Pancreatic lipase is the predominant mechanism of fat digestion in the alimentary system; its inhibition is associated with decreased fat absorption. CES1 is present at lower levels in the gut than CES2 (P23141), but predominates in the liver, where it is responsible for the hydrolysis of many aliphatic, aromatic and steroid esters. Hormone-sensitive lipase is also a relatively non-selective esterase associated with steroid ester hydrolysis and triglyceride metabolism, particularly in adipose tissue. Endothelial lipase is secreted from endothelial cells and regulates circulating cholesterol in high density lipoproteins.</p>
        <p>In vitro analysis suggested IP 3 and IP 4 were poor substrates for SKIP, synaptojanin 1 and synaptojanin 2, but suggested that PIP 2 and PIP 3 were more efficiently hydrolysed [422].</p>
        <p>Enzymes Inositol phosphate turnover Inositol monophosphatase</p>
        <p>Inositol monophosphatase (E.C. 3.1.3.25, IM-Pase, myo-inositol-1(or 4)-phosphate phosphohydrolase) is a magnesium-dependent homodimer which hydrolyses myoinositol monophosphate to generate myo-inositol and phosphate.</p>
        <p>Glycerol may be a physiological phosphate acceptor. Li + is a nonselective un-competitive inhibitor more potent at IMPase 1 (pK i ca. 3.5, [324]; pIC 50 3.2, [359]) than IMPase 2 (pIC 50 1.8-2.1, [359]). IMPase activity may be inhibited competitively by L690330 (pK i 5.5, [324]), although the enzyme selectivity is not yet established. Comments THI (2-Acetyl-5-tetrahydroxybutyl imidazole) inhibits the enzyme activity in intact cell preparations [426].</p>
        <p>Bigaud M et al.</p>
        <p>Thyroid hormone turnover</p>
        <p>The thyroid hormones triiodothyronine and thyroxine, usually abbreviated as triiodothyronine and T 4 , respectively, are synthesized in the thyroid gland by sequential metabolism of tyrosine residues in the glycosylated homodimeric protein thyroglobulin (TG, P01266) under the influence of the haem-containing protein iodide peroxidase. Iodide peroxidase/TPO is a haem-containing enzyme, from the same structural family as eosinophil peroxidase (EPX, P11678), lactoperoxidase (LPO, P22079) and myeloperoxidase (MPO, P05164). Circulating thyroid hormone is bound to thyroxine-binding globulin (SERPINA7, P05543).</p>
        <p>These are 1 TM selenoproteins that remove an iodine from T 4 (3,3',5,5'-tetraiodothyronine) to generate triiodothyronine (3,3',5-triiodothyronine, a more potent agonist at thyroid hormone receptors) or rT 3 (rT3, 3,3',5'-triiodothyronine, a relatively inactive analogue). DIO1 is also able to deiodinate RT3 to form 3,3'-diidothyronine (T 2 ). Iodotyrosine deiodinase is a 1TM homodimeric enzyme.</p>
        <p>The hypoxia inducible factor (HIF) is a transcriptional complex that is involved in oxygen homeostasis [429]. At normal oxygen levels, the alpha subunit of HIF (HIF-1α) is targeted for degradation by prolyl hydroxylation by the PHD proteins 1-3 (HIF-PHs) whch are 2-oxoglutarate (2OG) oxygenases responsible for the post-translational modification of a specific proline in each of the oxygen-dependent degradation (ODD) domains of HIF-1α.</p>
        <p>Hydroxylated HIFs are then targeted for proteasomal degradation via the von Hippel-Lindau ubiquitination complex [232]. Under hypoxic conditions, the hydroxylation reaction is blunted which results in decreased HIF degradation. The surviving HIFs are then available to translocate to the nucleus where they heterodimerize with HIF-1β, effecting increased expression of hypoxia-inducible genes.</p>
        <p>HIF-PH enzymes are being investigated as pharmacological targets as their inhibition mimics the hypoxic state and switches on transcription of genes associated with processes such as erythropoiesis and vasculogenesis [142]. Small molecule HIF-PH inhibitors are in clinical trial as novel therapies for the amelioration of anemia associated with chronic kidney disease [46].</p>
        <p>Nomenclature egl-9 family hypoxia-inducible factor 2 egl-9 family hypoxia-inducible factor 1 egl-9 family hypoxia-inducible factor 3 [66]. Protein farnesyltransferase catalyses the post-translational formation of a thioether linkage between the C-1 of an isoprenyl group and a cysteine residue fourth from the C-terminus of a protein (ie to the CaaX motif, where 'a' is an aliphatic amino acid and 'X' is usually serine, thionine, alanine or glutamine; leucine for EC 2.5.1.59) [156]. Farnesyltransferase is a dimer, composed of an alpha and beta subunit and requires Mg 2+ and Zn 2+ ions as cofactors. The active site is located between the subunits. Prenylation creates a hydrophobic domain on protein tails which acts as a membrane anchor. Substrates of the prenyltransferases include Ras, Rho, Rab, other Ras-related small GTP-binding proteins, G-protein γ-subunits, nuclear lamins, centromeric proteins and many proteins involved in visual signal transduction.</p>
        <p>In relation to the causative association between oncogenic Ras proteins and cancer, farnesyltransferase has become an important mechanistic drug discovery target. Overview: In humans, the peptidyl arginine deiminases (PADIs; HGNC family link) are a family of five enzymes, PADI1-4 and PADI6. PADIs catalyze the deimination of protein L-arginine residues to L-citrulline and ammonia. The human isozymes exhibit tissue-specific expression patterns [244].</p>
        <p>Enzymes 3.6.5.2 Small monomeric GTPases RAS subfamily</p>
        <p>The RAS proteins (HRAS, NRAS and KRAS) are small membrane-localised G protein-like molecules of 21 kd. They act as an on/off switch linking receptor and non-receptor tyrosine kinase activation to downstream cytoplasmic or nuclear events. Binding of GTP activates the switch, and hydrolysis of the GTP to GDP inactivates the switch. The RAS proto-oncogenes are the most frequently mutated class of proteins in human cancers. Common mutations compromise the GTP-hydrolysing ability of the proteins causing constitutive activation [457], which leads to increased cell proliferation and decreased apoptosis [550]. Because of their importance in oncogenic transformation these proteins have become the targets of intense drug discovery effort [23].</p>
        <p>Searchable</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>i 9.4)</p>
        <p>[252]</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp M1: Aminopeptidase N 6037 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.i 9.4) [270] -Rabbit, captopril (pK i 8.4) [331], zofenopril Selective inhibitors perindoprilat (pIC 50 9) [67], cilazaprilat (pIC 50 8.7) [514] -Rabbit, imidaprilat (pIC 50 8.7) [409], lisinopril-tryptophan (C-domain assay) (pIC 50 8.2) [515], RXP-407 (N-domain selective inhibition) (pIC 50 8.1) [434], fosinoprilat (pIC 50 8) [106] -Rabbit, enalaprilat (pIC 50 7.5) [79], benazeprilat (pIC 50 6.6) [282] Comments Reports of ACE GPI hydrolase activity [265] have been refuted [283]</p>
        <p>M10: Matrix metallopeptidase</p>
        <p>Overview: Matrix metalloproteinases (MMP) are calcium-and zinc-dependent proteinases regulating the extracellular matrix and are often divided (e.g.</p>
        <p>[501]</p>
        <p>) on functional and structural bases into gelatinases, collagenases, stromyelinases and matrilysins, as well as membrane type-MMP (MT-MMP).</p>
        <p>Comments: A number of small molecule 'broad spectrum' inhibitors of MMP have been described, including marimastat and batimastat. Tissue inhibitors of metalloproteinase (TIMP) proteins are endogenous inhibitors acting to chelate MMP proteins: TIMP1 (TIMP1, P01033), TIMP2 (TIMP2, P16035), TIMP3 (TIMP3, P35625), TIMP4 (TIMP4, Q99727)</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp M10: Matrix</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp M28: Aminopeptidase Y 6039 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp T1: Proteasome 6041 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Dimethylarginine dimethylaminohydrolases 6047 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.i 7.2) [548] -Rat Selective inhibitors -1400W (pIC 50 8.2) [168], 2-amino-4-methylpyridine (pIC 50 7.4) [131], PIBTU (pIC 50 7.</p>
        <p>Enzymes</p>
        <p>Carboxylases and decarboxylases Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Carboxylases and decarboxylases 6048 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.Comments -Citrate and other dicarboxylic acids are allosteric activators of acetyl-CoA carboxylase. Citrate and other dicarboxylic acids are allosteric activators of acetyl-CoA carboxylase. Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Carboxylases 6049 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.13354/full Loss-of-function mutations in γ-glutamyl carboxylase are associated with clotting disorders. Comments: Overview: The decarboxylases generate CO 2 and the indicated products from acidic substrates, requiring pyridoxal phosphate or pyruvic acid as a co-factor. Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Decarboxylases 6050 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.13354/full -Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Decarboxylases 6051 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.13354/full</p>
        <p>Tyrosine may also be metabolized in the liver by tyrosine transaminase to generate 4-hydroxyphenylpyruvic acid, which can be further metabolized to homogentisic acid. TAT is a homodimer, where loss-of-function mutations are associated with type II tyrosinemia.</p>
        <p>AADC is a homodimer. Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Catecholamine turnover 6053 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.13354/full Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Overview: Ceramides are a family of sphingophospholipids synthesized in the endoplasmic reticulum, which mediate cell stress responses, including apoptosis, autophagy and senescence, Serine palmitoyltransferase generates 3-ketosphinganine, which is reduced to sphinganine (dihydrosphingosine). N-Acylation allows the formation of dihydroceramides, which are subsequently re-duced to form ceramides. Once synthesized, ceramides are trafficked from the ER to the Golgi bound to the ceramide transfer protein, CERT (COL4A3BP, Q9Y5P4). Ceramide can be metabolized via multiple routes, ensuring tight regulation of its cellular levels. Addition of phosphocholine generates sphingomyelin while carbohydrate is added to form glucosyl-or galactosylceramides.</p>
        <p>Ceramidase re-forms sphingosine or sphinganine from ceramide or dihydroceramide. Phosphorylation of ceramide generates ceramide phosphate. The determination of accurate kinetic parameters for many of the enzymes in the sphingolipid metabolic pathway is complicated by the lipophilic nature of the substrates.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Serine palmitoyltransferase 6055 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.13354/full</p>
        <p>Overview: This family of enzymes, also known as sphingosine N-acyltransferase, is located in the ER facing the cytosol with an as-yet undefined topology and stoichiometry. Ceramide synthase in vitro is sensitive to inhibition by the fungal derived toxin, fumonisin B1.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Sphingolipid ½ 4 -desaturase</p>
        <p>Comments: DEGS1 activity is inhibited by a number of natural products, including curcumin and ½ 9 -tetrahydrocannabinol</p>
        <p>[130]</p>
        <p>. Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Sphingolipid ½ 4 -desaturase 6057 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.13354/</p>
        <p>-</p>
        <p>Sphingomyelin phosphodiesterase</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Overview: Protein FAN</p>
        <p>[2]</p>
        <p>and polycomb protein EED</p>
        <p>[383]</p>
        <p>allow coupling between TNF receptors and neutral sphingomyelinase phosphodiesterases. Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Ceramide glucosyltransferase 6059 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.13354/full</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>34: 111-8 [PMID:24977485] Ito M et al. (2014) New insight into the structure, reaction mechanism, and biological functions of neutral ceramidase. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1841: 682-91 [PMID:24064302] Saied EM et al. (2014) Small molecule inhibitors of ceramidases. Cell. Physiol. Biochem. 34: 197-212 [PMID:24977492] Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Exchange protein activated by cyclic AMP (Epac) --Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Phosphodiesterases, 3',5'-cyclic nucleotide 6066 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.13354/full Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Phosphodiesterases, 3',5'-cyclic nucleotide 6067 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.13354/full Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Phosphodiesterases, 3',5'-</p>
        <p>Overview:</p>
        <p>The cytochrome P450 enzyme family (CYP450), E.C.</p>
        <p>1.14.</p>
        <p>-.-, were originally defined by their strong absorbance at 450 nm due to the reduced carbon monoxide-complexed haem component of the cytochromes. They are an extensive family of haem-containing monooxygenases with a huge range of both en-dogenous and exogenous substrates. Listed below are the human enzymes; their relationship with rodent CYP450 enzyme activities is obscure in that the species orthologue may not mediate metabolism of the same substrates. Although the majority of CYP450 enzyme activities are concentrated in the liver, the extra-hepatic enzyme activities also contribute to patho/physiological processes. Genetic variation of CYP450 isoforms is widespread and likely underlies a significant proportion of the individual variation to drug administration. Further family members are included on the online database at ÛÛÛº Ù ØÓÈÀ ÊÅ Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>lauric acid to 12-hydroxylauric acid Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp CYP11, CYP17, CYP19, CYP20 and CYP21 families 6072 Full Contents of ConciseGuide: http://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/bph.13354/full Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp CYP24, CYP26 Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp CYP39, CYP46</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.50 8.1)</p>
        <p>[17]</p>
        <p>, diclofenac (pIC 50 7.9)</p>
        <p>[556], meclofenamic acid (pIC 50 7.</p>
        <p>3)</p>
        <p>[247]</p>
        <p>,</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Phosphatidylinositol-4-phosphate 3-</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Type I PIP kinases (1-phosphatidylinositol-4-</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp Type II PIP kinases (1-phosphatidylinositol-5-</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>M. (2011) Carboxylesterase 1 (Ces1): from monocyte marker to major player. J Clin Pathol 64: 107-109 [PMID:21177752] Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Comments: Polymorphisms in either of the genes encoding these enzymes have been linked with bipolar disorder</p>
        <p>[443,444,540]</p>
        <p>. Disruption of the gene encoding IMPase 1, but not IMPase 2, appears to mimic the effects of Li + in mice</p>
        <p>[97,98]</p>
        <p>.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>terolemia. Cardiol Rev 17: 70-6 [PMID:19367148] Zhang H et al. (2014) Cholesterol and lipoprotein metabolism: Early Career Committee contribution. Arterioscler. Thromb. Vasc. Biol. 34: 1791-4 [PMID:25142876] van der Burgh R et al. (2012) Mevalonate kinase deficiency, a metabolic autoinflammatory disease. Clin. Immunol. [PMID:23110805]</p>
        <p>Nucleoside synthesis and metabolism</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.</p>
        <p>Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp 2.4.2.30 poly(ADP-ribose)</p>
        <p>database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.Searchable database: http://www.guidetopharmacology.org/index.jsp 5.99.1.</p>
        <p>Further Reading Cooper DM et al. (2014) Adenylate cyclase-centred microdomains. Biochem. J. 462: 199-213 [PMID:25102028] Derbyshire ER et al. (2012) Structure and regulation of soluble guanylate cyclase. Annu. Rev. Biochem. 81: 533-59 [PMID:22404633] Francis SH et al. (2011) Mammalian cyclic nucleotide phosphodiesterases: molecular mechanisms and physiological functions. Physiol. Rev. 91: 651-90 [PMID:21527734] Nicol X et al. (2014) Routes to cAMP: shaping neuronal connectivity with distinct adenylate cyclases. Eur. J. Neurosci. 39: 1742-51 [PMID:24628976] Schmidt M et al. (2013) Exchange protein directly activated by cAMP (epac): a multidomain cAMP mediator in the regulation of diverse biological functions. Pharmacol. Rev. 65: 670-709 [PMID:23447132] Steegborn C. (2014) Structure, mechanism, and regulation of soluble adenylyl cyclases -similarities and differences to transmembrane adenylyl cyclases. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1842: 2535-47 [PMID:25193033]</p>
        <p>The authors state that there are no conflicts of interest to declare.</p>
        <p>Overview: Haem oxygenase (heme,hydrogen-donor:oxygen oxidoreductase (α-methene-oxidizing, hydroxylating)), E.C.</p>
        <p>The existence of a third non-catalytic version of haem oxygenase, HO3, has been proposed, although this has been suggested to be a pseudogene [202]. The chemical tin protoporphyrin IX acts as a haem oxygenase inhibitor in rat liver with an IC 50 value of 11 nM [120].</p>
        <p>Abraham</p>
    </body>
</text>
</tei>
