<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc xml:id="_1"/>
<encodingDesc>
<appInfo>
<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-08-31T06:50+0000">
<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
</application>
</appInfo>
</encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<body>
<p>25 interventions for people with hearing loss. 26 Method: Four intervention studies of people with hearing loss were examined: two auditory 27 training studies, one working memory training study, and one study of multimedia 28 educational support.</p>
<p>There is an ever increasing use of personal computers and the internet to provide healthcare 40 and health-related information (Brouwer et al., 2011), and hearing healthcare is no exception.</p>
<p>diagnosis (Krumm, Ribera, &amp; Klich, 2007), and interventions such as auditory training 44 (Ferguson, Henshaw, Clark, &amp; Moore, 2014;Sweetow &amp; Henderson Sabes, 2006), PC and internet use, with poorer use seen in older people, women, and those with lower SES 75 (Henshaw, Clark, Kang, &amp; Ferguson, 2012). PC and internet use in the youngest group (50-76 54 years) was 85% and 36% respectively but was significantly lower in the oldest group (70-77 74 years) at 36% and 17%. These differences were consistent with other reports (Seybert &amp; 78 Lööf, 2010;Thoren, Öberg, Wänström, Andersson, &amp; Lunner, 2013). Current data on internet 79 use shows a year-on-year increase in 55-74 year olds (2010 =61%, 2012 = 70%, 2014 = 80 78%), suggesting teleaudiology will become more prevalent in this age group (UNECE, 81 2015) over the coming years.</p>
<p>There has been little published on the effect of hearing loss on PC and internet use in older 83 adults. In our study of PC and internet use (Henshaw et al., 2012) Ferguson, 2014;WMT, Henshaw &amp; Ferguson, 2013;MES, Ferguson et al., in review). Three 104 studies (AT1, AT2, MES) showed positive results, with at least moderate effect sizes. The 105 WMT results are currently unpublished.</p>
<p>Computer skills were rated by participants on a validated three-category scale (Never used a 107 computer, Beginner or Competent, see Henshaw et al., 2012). The percentage of participants 108 in each category provides a measure of accessibility in terms of PC skills (Table 1). For the Nevertheless, access to IT and mobile technologies for the over-55s is increasing, and will 161 continue to increase over the coming years (Deloitte, 2014). There was no evidence that PC (Henshaw, McCormack, &amp; Ferguson, In press). In conclusion, the potential for 165 online applications to reach many people with hearing loss who cannot or will not access 166 conventional audiology services is substantial. Although there are currently some barriers to 167 internet access for a proportion of people with hearing loss, there is a clear need to develop 168 and future-proof internet-delivered applications. from the sale of the C2Hear RLOs. There will be no payment made to any individual member 180 of the research team.</p>
<p>85</p>
<p>those with moderate hearing difficulties showed less use. This suggests that potential uses of 86 tele-audiology in this age group, including early intervention such as auditory training, 89 102 results are described in more detail elsewhere (AT1,</p>
<p>Ferguson et al., 2014; AT2, Henshaw &amp;</p>
<p>Telehealth applications in audiology, or tele-audiology, include hearing screening(Smits,</p>
<p>Merkus, &amp; Houtgast, 2006;Swanepoel, Myburgh, Howe, Mahomed, &amp; Eikelboom, 2014),</p>
<p>American Journal of Audiology</p>
<p>We would like to thank our colleagues who made significant contributions to the intervention</p>
</body>
</text>
</tei> 