<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<tei xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
<teiHeader>
<fileDesc xml:id="_1"/>
<encodingDesc>
<appInfo>
<application version="0.8.0" ident="GROBID" when="2024-08-31T06:47+0000">
<ref target="https://github.com/kermitt2/grobid">A machine learning software for extracting information from scholarly documents</ref>
</application>
</appInfo>
</encodingDesc>
</teiHeader>
<text xml:lang="en">
<body>
<p>The aim of this research was to determine the functions of code-switching when used by a lecturer in teaching her students during interactions in the teaching and learning of English. This research was conducted at one of the campuses in Serang Banten. This qualitative research used the methods for ethnography of communication. The techniques and procedures for data collection used observation, recordings and transcriptions. Based on data analysis, the use of code switching in the ESL classroom was used to facilitate interactions when learning was taking place. Based on the analysis, the functions of code switching of the lecturer when interacting with her in the class are: (1) clarification, (2) reiteration or repetition, (3) explanation, (4) asking, ( 5) translation, ( 6) checking for understanding, ( 7) emphasizing a language element, (8) making inferences, ( 9) developing vocabulary, (10) class discussions of student tasks, (11) giving feedback, (12) aiding memorization, (13) class management and ( 14) entertainment and general communications. The result of this research is expected to be useful especially for teachers in the field of language to understand the functions and the effectiveness of code switching in the classroom.</p>
<p>Code switching in the sociolinguistic field of foreign language teaching studies was a major subject of scientific studies in the past. Recently, code-switching has again attracted a considerable amount of attention. It has become an interesting phenomenon to study in particular the usage of language in society because it is part of the development processes and the use of multiple languages (i.e. bilingualism and multilingualism). About the choice of code, code switching is used by people who are bilingual and multilingual (Wardhaugh, 2006).</p>
<p>The reasons cannot be separated from the influence of linguistic diversity in a community of people who intermingle to form a mixture of language that they can understand. For example, a group who speaks Language A mix with the people who speaks Language B, when both communities interact, naturally these people develop some form of code switching. In fact, that is show the English language developed from its Germanic origins; and has words in it from Latin, French, Arabic, Tamil and many other languages including Malay.</p>
<p>Hence, the use of code switching usually occurs during foreign language teachinglearning processes especially when studying English based on the different backgrounds and reasons (Yusuf, 2009). Sert (2005, p. 1) states "in ELT classrooms, code switching comes into use either in the teachers' or the students' discourse". Code switching exists in English classrooms and has many code variations.</p>
<p>In the case of Indonesia, English language, even though treated as a foreign language, is a compulsory subject in all school levels. A statement given by TESOL (2008, p. 1) affirms that "English is seen less and less as a "foreign" language, and more as an additional language. In other words, learning English is no longer viewed as something optional, but essential". This is especially so since all of Indonesia's neighbouring countries and major trading partners and international organisations to which Indonesia belongs to use primarily English as a means of communication.</p>
<p>In the end, one of the goals of EFL (English Foreign Language) teacher is to have the students speak English as much as possible, especially when they are in the English classroom. Hancock (1997, p. 217) further stresses "to promote communicative competence, learners must get practice in communicative exchanges in the classroom". So, to improve communication competence in English, teachers must do more exercises in English in the classroom. For that the English teachers should also be able to speak English fluently when teaching-learning students so that learning is effective. In reality both teachers and students still perform code switching or code mixing even at the highest levels of education for various needs and objectives.</p>
<p>Various researchers have studied code switching that occurs in a bilingual classroom over the last two decades. The research began with educational research into the classroom interaction styles of language teachers. The study of code switching has generally been done within a sociolinguistic framework where researchers and linguists study the communications symptoms that occur in bilingual and multilingual societies. Code switching can be examined from various viewpoints such as the form, location, patterns, and functions of code switching and code mixing itself. In this case the researcher describes and discusses code-switching based on the functions which it serves an English classroom.</p>
<p>Bilingualism, or as we more often hear the term bilingual, means the ability to use two languages or language codes. Many sociolinguistics research studies that examine the issues of language codes are closely related to studies of bilingualism. Explanations about the concept of bilingualism are always changing. The term was first introduced by Bloomfield (1935, p. 56) who says bilingualism as the ability to use two languages or to have "native like control of two languages". Moreover, Milroy and Gordon (2003) say the instance of switching code is the use of multiple languages alternately by bilingual speakers.</p>
<p>Bilingual and multilingual people generally tend to switch language codes during their conversations. Code switching that occurs in the community is often regarded as a strategy for use in conversations. Sometimes this strategy is used in terms of stylistic influence, which relates to its use for reinforcing or weakening speech acts such as requests, denials, switching topics, elaborations or comments, validations, or clarifications (Heller, 2007). The use of code has a value of naturalness for particular speech events within the community of bilingual speakers.</p>
<p>Many experts have given clear definition of code switching and its difference from other terms. Among them is Gumperz (1982, p. 59), who states that code switching is "the juxtaposition within the same speech exchange of passages of speech belonging to two different language/grammatical systems or sub-systems". Milroy and Gordon (2003, p. 209) have also argued that "the term 'code-switching' can describe a range of language (or dialect) alternation and mixing phenomena whether within the same conversation, the same turn, or the same sentence-utterance". More recently, Sebba, Mahootian, and Jonsson (2012, p. 68) have given a far simpler definition of code switching, stating that "code-switching -the alternating use of two (or more) languages -is a natural occurrence in the speech of bilingual individuals". Milroy and Gordon (2003) see that code switching as a manner or form of communication that is common in a bilingual or multilingual society using a number of different languages. By contrast, in the process of bilingual education, code switching is more managerial. For instance, in the learning process, switching of code acts more as a tool to manage and facilitate interaction and learning. Heller (2007) plainly says that code switching is the process of using more than one language in one episode of communication. In this case, it requires the balancing mastery of two or more languages by speakers who switch codes.</p>
<p>Code switching in a foreign language classroom has recently been the subject of considerable study and debate. When researchers address the issue, especially the use or the roles of the L1 (first language) and the TL (target language) or L2 (second language), there appear to be two opposing language attitudes between them, either use the target language exclusively or tolerate and get benefits from code switching. According to (Macaro, 1997), the switching to L1 necessarily serves some basic functions which may be beneficial in the foreign language learning environment. However, to get main goal in learning a language, the lecturer has to create a situation for student to speak in English in the classroom (Rahayu, 2016).</p>
<p>There are many functions of code-switching in the teaching-learning process. According to Reyes (2004, p. 84), they are: (1) speech representation, (2) imitate quotation, (3) turn accommodation, (4) topic shift, (5) situation switch, (6) insistence, (7) giving an emphasis, (8) clarification or persuasion, (9) persons specification, (10) question shift, and (11) as a discourse maker. An additional function by Mattsson and Burenhult (1999, p. 9) is repetition, where "the repetition in the first language (L1) can be either partial or full and is often expanded with further information, but more frequently code switching is used as a repetition of the previously uttered sentences".</p>
<p>This study is a qualitative research with the intent to collect process, analyse, and present data objectively about the occurrence of code switching in teaching English to students of the English Department at the State Islamic Institute "Mulana Sultan Hasanuddin" in Banten. This study used an ethnographic method for study of communication based on Hymes (1996) and was further developed by Saville-Troike (2003) with a pragmatic approach.</p>
<p>The primary data was the phenomenon of code switching in the teaching-learning interactions that occurred in the teaching and learning processes of a class at the department. The source was from a lecturer and her students' interactions in the English classroom. Meanwhile, the source of secondary data was books and documents relevant to the focus of the research.</p>
<p>Recording was done to obtain data in the field. The procedure for collecting data was through observation, recordings, and transcriptions. The steps to analyse the data included creating categories based on the various communicative situations, communicative events and communicative actions.</p>
<p>The results in terms of the functions of code-switching from English to Indonesian appear to support previous findings, which suggest that the switching to L1 necessarily serves some basic functions which may be beneficial in the foreign language learning environment (Macaro, 1997). The data from the classroom recordings reinforces the views on the functional uses and enriches the data from other reviews. This section lists the functions of code switching to Indonesian and then looks at some samples from the data to illustrate the functions of code-switching that occurred between the lecturer and her students.</p>
<p>Based on the analysis, the functions of code switching the lecturer and her students were found to be: (1) clarification, (2) reiteration or repetition, (3) explanation, (4) asking, (5) translation, (6) checking for understanding, (7) emphasizing of a language element, (8) making inferences, (9) developing vocabulary, (10) class discussions of student' tasks, (11) giving feedback, (12) aiding memorization, (13) class management, and (14) entertainment and general communications.</p>
<p>The first is the function of clarification; it was conducted by the teacher and the students to provide clarification or confirmation of an explanation, or of information, or of questions, or of a statement, in order to avoid misunderstanding in terms of capturing the intent of the English. The use of code switching becomes the means that the teacher uses to confirm or clarify her meaning of communication. So, she feels the need to transfer the code into Indonesian for clarification of her previous converses in English.</p>
<p>The second is the function of reiteration or repetition. In doing the code switching for reiteration, the teacher repeats the speech in Indonesian in the form of a sentence or phrase. Repetition was done to align the meanings in the two different languages (i.e. Indonesian and English), so that the students in the interaction could gain a better understanding of the words or phrases spoken by the teacher. Furthermore, Mattsson and Burenhult (1999) reveal that the importance of repetition in code switching is to emphasize the message to be delivered following a quotation. Gumperz (1982) and Brice (2000) also emphasize that one function of repetition in code switching is to check understanding.</p>
<p>The third is the function of explanation or redirection of code made by the teacher in the interaction when there are lessons that needed further explanation, and thus, to explain the earlier information given in English, the explanation is preceded in Indonesian. An excerpt of when the teacher was teaching grammar is shown in E1 (E refers to excerpt), the redirection of code is bolded: E1: Ya, kata subject bertemu dengan kata subject lagi, maka menjadi compound subject. Kata verb dari kata kerja bertemu dengan kata kerja lagi disebut compound verb. Okay, Tika… [Yes, a subject meets a subject, so it becomes compound subject. A verb for an action word meets another verb so it is called compound verb. Okay, Tika…]</p>
<p>In the conversation in E1, the teacher code switches to Indonesian. In this sentence, she did not only try to explain the theory but also provided the answer to the student's previous question on what is a compound subject.</p>
<p>The fourth is the function for asking questions. When the teacher interacted with the base code English, and then a student asked a question using Indonesian not English and so the lecturer used code switching when answering the student's question and asked him back another question. This is as shown in the following example (L is for lecturer and S is for student). E2: L: Iya…never mind ya because practice makes perfect. Kira kira ada yang kurang tepat pengejaannya? Chicago or Cicago tadi? [Yes, never mind, because practice makes perfect. So is there something wrong with the pronunciation? Chicago or is it Cicago? S: Cicago… L: Chicago or Cicago? S: Chicago.</p>
<p>In E2, it can be seen clearly that despite the lecturer started off in English, she switched to Indonesian to present her question. And so, in this case, the function of code switching was to ask a question.</p>
<p>Translation is the fifth function found in data. This form of code switching from English to Indonesian is done by the speakers to translate a statement or question because they felt that it needed translation to make the listener better understand the meaning of the statement or question in order to avoid misunderstanding.</p>
<p>The sixth function is to check understanding. This form of code switching from English into Indonesian or vice versa has a function to review material that has been taught previously. It was also done by the lecturer to check for students' understanding on a matter that has been taught-learned in the classroom as a benchmark for determining the level of students' understanding of the material. E3: L: Okay, sometimes a concluding sentence reminds the readers of the points in the topic sentence. Di ulang lagi di ulang lagi ya…sama aja dengan yang pertama kali di pelajari dulu ya. So di pharaphrase ya…kalimat yang di atas itu topic sentence-nya…topic sentence, supporting sentence…terus di akhir, nah, topic tadi di summary, di pharaphrase dengan bahasa yang berbeda…di pharaphrase. Jadi di singgung sedikit ya yang topic sentence nya tadi untuk dijadikan sebagai concluding sentence.</p>
<p>[Okay, sometimes a concluding sentence reminds the readers of the points in the topic sentence. You must repeat it and repeat it…it is similar to what you have learnt earlier. So you must paraphrase it…the sentence above it is the topic sentence…topic sentence, supporting sentence…then at the end, the topic must be summarized, paraphrase it in different wordings…paraphrase it. So mention a bit about the topic sentence as the concluding sentence.]</p>
<p>In E3, it can be concluded that the explanation was meant to review the materials taught before. In addition, there is an expression that the material had been previously studied in the expression 'Di ulang lagi di ulang lagi ya…sama aja dengan yang pertama kali di pelajari dulu ya' [You must repeat it and repeat it…it is similar to what you have learnt earlier]. So the lecturer also reviews the material by code switching into Indonesian but she still uses the basic English codes when mentioning terms related to the lecture material.</p>
<p>The seventh function is for emphasizing some elements of language. Macaro (1997, p. 68) says "important messages can be reinforced or emphasized when they are transmitted in the L1". This form of code-switching also occurred in the classroom interactions between the lecturer and students. The lecturer tried to emphasize the elements of language specifically related to teaching materials in English, so she felt the need to code switch to avoid misunderstanding between her and the students. This was so that they had the same understanding of specific linguistic elements related to the material. Possibly because the linguistic elements are theoretical, therefore, the lecturer felt the need to code switch into Indonesian so the students could better understand her.</p>
<p>The eighth function is for making inferences. This code switching is done for functionality to make conclusions, which means that the lecturer in this study used basic codes in English when explaining the materials. However, when concluding the lessons, she explained them by code switching into Indonesian. So, the function of the code switching here was to make or to emphasize conclusions or inferences.</p>
<p>The ninth function is for developing vocabulary. This form of code-switching is done when the lecturer and the students were discussing about vocabulary. There were many times when the words had to be interpreted or translated into the first language so that the students could better comprehend English words to develop their vocabulary.</p>
<p>The tenth function is to discuss the students' assignment. This form of code switching was done by the lecturer to discuss the assignments that she had given to her students. To have her students fully understand her instructions, she code switched into Indonesian. Students would also do the same for clarification on the assignments given so that they could grasp the instructions correctly. This was also done when discussing the students' progress with her.</p>
<p>The eleventh function is to give feedback. In the data, this was found when the lecturer required the students to give her feedback on the lessons. This importance of code switching here was to determine the extent of students' understanding on the material being studied. It was also necessary to know the parts they have mastered the parts that needed improvement. Code switching enabled both the lecturer and the students to fully capture the heart of their feedback discussions.</p>
<p>The twelfth function is to remember or memorize. It was common in class that the lecturer frequently reminded the students about the materials, tasks, rules or roles that the students may have forgotten about, or otherwise not done. In such conversations code switching often occurred.</p>
<p>The thirteenth function is to assist in managing the teaching-learning activities in the class. There were some activities in the class that did not require the process of transferring knowledge as their main aim, but to support the management of the class during learning. For example, to get the students to walk in an orderly way. This is as supported by Choong (2006, p. 2) who asserts that "some reasons for using the L1 in the classroom are to convey and check the comprehension of lexical or grammatical forms and meanings, to give directions, and to manage the class". In such conditions and with such interactions, the lecturer and students often switched code into Indonesian because they felt that the condition or situation is not part of the transfer of knowledge. An example is when a student came late to class, and the lecturer commented on the situation: E4: L: Ya di tahan tahanin aja lah. Next week you have to come earlier ya…biar gak di serobot orang lain.</p>
<p>[(You) have to be patient/strong. Next week you have to come earlier…so that other people do not take (your class).]</p>
<p>Here, the lecturer code switches to tell the students to arrive early in order to get a better classroom. She switched codes into Indonesian because she considered it more effective and efficient given the time which was not much. She did not want to spend much time for giving such instructions.</p>
<p>The last function, the fourteenth one, is for entertainment and general communications. Examples found in the data were such as to relieve boredom, to relieve tension or simply to better familiarize themselves with each other in the educational situation. Sometimes both the lecturer and students made jokes with each other and, and thus, when jesting they felt better using Indonesian.</p>
<p>In language teaching, in this case teaching the English language, there often appears the sociolinguistic phenomenon of code-switching, which is the use of two languages in a single interaction or event. In the teaching of English, the use of codeswitching into Indonesian occurs frequently in Indonesia. However, some experts disagree with code-switching because they perceive it to have low prestige and to lessen the emphasis on becoming fluent in English.</p>
<p>However, based on the results of this study, the use of code-switching in the language instruction has multiple functions that support an effective learning process. These functions include (1) clarification, (2) reiteration or repetition, (3) explanation, (4) asking, (5) translation, (6) checking for understanding, (7) emphasizing a language element, (8) making inferences, (9) developing vocabulary, (10) class discussions of student tasks, (11) giving feedback, (12) aiding memorization, (13) class management and ( 14) entertainment and general communications. Despite there are shortcomings in the conduct of this research, such as focusing on only one class, and one lecturer and her students, thus, this research is expected to be useful especially for teachers in the field of language to understand the functions and the effectiveness of code switching in the classroom.</p>
<p>Eva Fachriyah received her Doctoral degree in language education from Jakarta State University; her passion is in English teaching learning. She has been a lecturer for several years as an English lecturer at Serang Raya University in Banten. Her fields of interest include applied linguistics, teaching methods, and research. She has written for proceedings and local journals, and has also presented in several international and national conferences.</p>
</body>
</text>
</tei>